Within a day of changing the thumbnail,
that video went from [music] getting
a,000 views a day to 40,000 views a day.
>> That's Patty Galloway. He's responsible
for over 50 billion YouTube views. Red
Bull, Mr. Beast, the Philadelphia
[music] Eagles, and he even made his own
dog go viral.
>> Videos that have 10, 50, 100 million
views always [music] posed a question
that you have to click to answer. The
click part of the equation is 50% of
[music] the game.
>> He shows the exact systems behind the
videos you can't stop watching and why
attention is the only thing that
matters. If you can consistently [music]
go viral, like that is the most
important skill. It's so crucial you get
this next priority which is
50 billion views. The highest paid
YouTube strategist in the world. Worked
with Red Bull, Mr. Beast, the
Philadelphia Eagles. He claims he can
make any channel, any account go viral.
We're going to give you the full
playbook today.
So you walked into Red Bull's YouTube
channel. They're averaging 400,000 views
a video today over 9 million. What did
you find when you walked in?
>> YouTube strategy. It just wasn't being
applied. So, I think this is something
you see all the time with YouTube
channels with big brands. They treat
YouTube like it's just a place to host
videos, right? I call them Vimeo
creators because they're just like using
it as like a video hosting platform. And
I think consistently when I look at the
channels that we've managed to grow to
be the biggest channels in the world or
you know in that case like 10x 20x
viewership it's just putting emphasis
and putting time towards the things that
actually matter. So you know a lot of
people think YouTube is just you know
make a video shoot a video put it up you
know if it goes viral it goes viral. And
I think I believed this 10 years ago and
I've become more and more convinced of
it that virality can be engineered. It's
actually a lot more predictable than
people think. So when we come into a
channel like Rebel or any of the
channels we've worked with, it's about
like how can we look at the data? How
can we look at what they're doing and
actually predict virality for their
channel?
>> Yeah. It's not so much a strategy as
much as it is a framework. And guys,
this guy made his dog go viral. And even
the Philadelphia Eagles, like you look
at Red Bull, you look at a dog, you look
at the Eagles, and I mean you're
literally three, four, 5x more views on
the Philadelphia Eagles versus any other
NFL team. So, it really does kind of
apply anywhere. When you kind of look at
it from like a a macro perspective, what
are kind of those big buckets on how you
just look at YouTube in general? And
then we'll kind of like double click on
each.
>> Yeah. So, to me, I always like to say
YouTube is a click and watch platform,
right? And I think that's very different
to how again people really perceive it.
They just think of it as like, oh, you
just watch videos. But when you think
about it, you're scrolling a platform,
you're clicking. That's very different
to other platforms like Instagram,
Rails, Tik Tok. You're being served
things. You're watching things that are
being served to you. YouTube, you still
have that decision to make. At least
with long form, you have that choice to
make. So, I always think YouTube really
boils down to a few things. It boils
down to, can we come up with better
ideas than anyone else? Can we come up
with ideas that are going to travel and
go viral? Can we make those ideas really
clickable? So, can a lot of people click
those videos? And I do like to say that
the the click part of the equation is
kind of 50% of the game. And I always
shock people when I say, you know,
there's clients we work with where we'll
make 50 thumbnails for a video. And you
know, the person's just sort of standing
there going, "Oh, I I make one." I'm
like, "Yeah, we make 50." And we have
five designers working on different
concepts for just one video. And you
know, I think the click is a really
important part of the equation. Once you
have the click, well, what's important?
Well, they need to watch for as long as
possible. The YouTube algorithm values
kind of three things. People clicking,
people watching, and people being
satisfied. So, you need to make a
satisfying video that keeps people
watching for as long as possible and
then it just becomes a game of doing it
again. Long-term strategy like how can
you actually build momentum into like a
repeatable channel where you can keep
making videos that go viral. So, I think
if you take a step back, the reality is
is, you know, we're going to go through
the frameworks and principles to first
and foremost just make people click
because if they don't click, you could
create the greatest video of all time,
but you know, title, thumbnail, stuff
like that, then you're out of the game.
And then secondly, from a macro
perspective, I would just say retention.
just how do you keep them as long as
possible to feed the algorithm and
obviously just get more net new people
to watching the video? You've said
before that like virality is like the
most important skill to have nowadays.
That's like a fairly big claim. Um why
would you say that?
>> I think every other moat is dying in in
business in creative. It's even
interesting just driving through here,
driving through Hollywood Hills, right?
And like you're seeing all these offices
empty, right? all these traditional
media, you know, companies and Hollywood
and film production studios, they're
just lying empty. I think if you can own
distribution, you can build products in
any niche. And I always like to sort of
view it through the lens of like it's a
cliche, but I think attention right now
is what gas was or oil was to America in
like 1885. It's like if you have the
attention, you have the power. In the
last three months, I won't name the
names, but in the last three months,
I've had like huge politicians,
billionaires, hall of fame athletes
reach out to me and ask me about YouTube
and about making videos. And it's like
that wasn't happening 5 years ago. That
wasn't happening 10 years ago. And I was
even I was at dinner recently with my
friend. I just he was like, "What's like
a really bold claim you would stand by?"
And I was like, I think the next
president of the United States is going
to be who is the best at viral content
in 2028.
>> I said on episode, I don't even know
what it was, like 3, four with Nick
Shakford that I mean, I think Mr. Beast
is going to be the president if he wants
to be in 2036, just under the notion
that if a fraction of his followers vote
for him, like he would win over the
whole entire United States. So, I
completely agree with that. And like you
also see,
you know, people are buying these big
media companies under the notion that
they own distribution and attention and
they just want to sway people to make
decisions towards them. Like you saw
that with TVPN. I mean, it was purchased
for nine figures plus. Yeah. And you
know, TVPN is a podcast that's doing
what,
a,000 2,000 views an episode on YouTube.
Do you think open open AI paid $100
million for the podcast or do you think
they paid for the the brain of
understanding content and understanding
virality and you know John and Jordy
clearly have that brain? I think that's
what they bought.
>> Yeah. Clearly was like an aqua hire for
that and I think that also speaks to the
notion that they have it's not even a
big audience but it's a very small
valuable audience which we'll get into
right now that views aren't everything.
It's a lot in the beginning, but owning
a small concentrated audience that has
purchasing power, the ability to
influence is everything.
>> Yeah. And I I think on that point as
well, something really interesting I
bring up is maybe 10 years ago. I've
been doing this for 20 years. So I
uploaded my first video in 2006. So 20
years this year, I think it was July of
of 2006. So it's going to be 20 years
next month.
>> Insane.
>> And every single year since then, I've
posted videos on YouTube. You know, I
have multiple channels. I've had like 40
50 channels. People know me from the
channel, which is my own name. But
what's interesting is like I think maybe
eight, nine years ago, I was on this
radio show in Ireland, which is my home
country. And it's this radio show.
They're also like a big like publisher
in Ireland. And they're like, "How does
this make sense? Like, how do you make
money from this? How could anyone make
money from this?" And this is like, you
know, 10 years ago. And I'm like, "Oh,
like I'm doing 500,000 views every
episode." And they're like, "Yeah, how
does how do you make money from that?"
I'm like, "How many people tune in to
your biggest like show on TV?" And
they're like, "250, like 250, 100,000
people or 350,000 people per episode?"
I'm like, "How many employees do you
have for that episode?" They go, "11
150." I'm like, "It's me in my bedroom
and I'm getting similar viewership and
you think there's no way this can be
valuable." And back then it wasn't as
obvious. And now, you know, flash
forward to today, you know, I have one
of the highest grossing directors of all
time has reached out to me. one of uh
you know these Hollywood studios,
Netflix, all these different places are
just seeing the value of organic content
now.
>> Yeah. I also think too like you touched
on it. It's as a business you can have
very very low opex and scale this like
it might have been just you in your
bedroom filming it. Obviously you can
have higher production and go deeper
into that and it would be a little bit
more expensive but people are starting
to see just inputs outputs. You could
have a very very small team and get tens
of millions of views and then just build
a business or a service on top of that.
Yeah, I've seen some of the most
disgusting profit margins ever with
creator companies and some of the worst
to be fair. Like it is it can be a
little bit of a barbell where like some
people are reinvesting every single
penny and you know going all out trying
to go viral trying to be the next Mr.
Beast. But then there's other people on
the end of the spectrum who you've never
heard of that operate in a little niche
and they have like two employees and
they're doing 15 million a year from
content. Like I know two people that do
that.
>> Yeah. I mean, I come from the e-com
space where like ebida is as low as like
5 10 15%. I feel like on media it could
be as high as like 90 95%. I would say
as low as like 50% if you want to push
the initiative on kind of other things.
But like you could definitely run a 50%
ebot business in media. It's [__]
insane.
>> 100%.
>> I want to double click now and just
start just overall into how you kind of
come up with ideas because that's kind
of obviously the first kind of touch
point. We're going to pop up kind of
here, guys, about this kind of what what
you call it is this ceiling problem.
Most people think they have a content
problem, but you think it's more of an
idea kind of problem. So, I'd love for
you to walk through like how they should
be looking at that.
>> Yeah, I always like this visual because
I think there are these three circles.
There are all the viewers you could
reach, there's the ceiling that your
idea imposes on the amount of viewers
you can reach, and then there's your
execution. And you actually need to look
at all three of those things at once
because, you know, first looking at the
actual all viewers you could reach.
Well, that's defined by the niche you're
in, by the market you're operating in.
You know, like lo and behold, like a
knitting niche has a smaller TAM than
like a Mr. Beast type channel, right?
So, the actual market you're in has a
huge impact on that. I always like to
say that like the bigger TAMs are a lot
more competitive, but there's obviously
more potential upside. smaller towns
where you have like, you know, smaller
niches, you can sort of build more
momentum, but then you do reach that
ceiling. But regardless of the niche,
your actual idea itself can just set a
ceiling. And people often just pick
ideas that when I look at them, I'm just
like, why did you think most people in
your niche would watch this? And they're
like, I didn't. I just thought it was
interesting. And I'm like, I understand
that, but if you're trying to build a
great YouTube channel, like you need to
look at videos that you think can reach
as far into your niche as possible and
and take up as much of that circle as
possible. So, you know, going back even
to your earlier question about what do
you do when you go into channels, I
think so much of it is saying like how
do we make the market we're operating in
bigger and then how do we come up with
ideas that reach further into that
market and then how do we make sure our
execution is good enough so our idea
travels as far as it should. I'd love
for you to give any type of kind of
simple idea where maybe it was like a
catastrophically low kind of idea but
someone was very talented and then you
opened it up into kind of a new format
or a bigger idea. anything you can kind
of point to there to kind of have people
visualize big ideas versus small ideas?
>> So, there was this channel that we
worked with through our training program
a couple years ago. Astrophotography
and astrophotography is kind of niche,
right? Taking photos of like the Milky
Way, right? It's pretty niche. He was
doing like a thousand 2,000 views a
video and you know it was like shoot his
videos would be like reviewing the new
telescope that he bought for
astrophotography or like teaching people
how to shoot you know the Milky Way or
whatever and it's all like
>> super small and technical to a small
town.
>> Yeah. Like no one really cares. And
during our training he he uploaded a
video which was like shooting a Milky
Way at like different with different
cameras. So like with an iPhone versus
an expensive camera or at different time
horizons like in 10 minutes versus an
hour versus 100 hours. You know there
was this video on YouTube that went
viral which was like 10 second haircut
versus 10-minute haircut versus 10hour
haircut something like that. And you
know you can take a niche an idea like
that and say well what would that look
like in astrophotography and it turns
out it looked like something really
interesting. And that video got I think
two or three million views. So it is
amazing how many small niche channels
that we have worked with that you would
think the TAM is like a few thousand
viewers but when you actually make it
broadly appealing you can go a lot
further. One of the most viral videos on
YouTube over the last few years was I
built a wildlife pond in my backyard. It
has like 25 million views, 30 million
views or something. And you know the
niche technically is wildlife ponds but
like imagine you were like a full guide
on how to build a wildlife pond or how
to like install your pond lining for
your wildlife pond. It's like 10,000
views maybe, Tam. But when you go with
that bigger, broader angle, you can you
can unlock so much more views.
>> Guys, we're going to go through all
different ways to kind of ideate ideas
and formats and all different ways to
kind of remix different things. So, if
the ideas are the ceiling, what would
you say is kind of the floor? Like what
is how do you look kind of through that
lens?
>> I think floor is it's an interesting
word. I think like
I kind of think that the floor is
basically like your audience. If the way
I like to think about floor is if you
posted a trash video, how many of your
viewers would watch? So when I work with
channels, I'm trying to figure out
ceiling and floor. It's like let's think
about the worst video we could possibly
post. Like if we literally, this is a
bit dramatic, but if we literally just
posted like a video that was titled
video one and a picture of our face, how
many viewers would that get? To me,
that's the floor. That's like the the
most dedicated viewers that would watch
you no matter what is kind of the floor
and then everything above that is like
our execution determines how far we can
go.
>> So you would say idea is kind of the
ceiling and then the floor would be kind
of the lowest execution versus your a
thousand Drew fans like the stickiest
fans that no matter what you put up
would would would watch it.
>> Exactly. Makes a lot of sense. Um
TAM is a word that we talk about a lot.
We have a lot of you know ecom operators
on here now. I feel like a lot of people
look at a niche and they're just like,
"Hey, this is a niche. It's a small
town. It can't hit a lot of people." Are
you basically saying that no matter
what, if you just think of a big idea,
you can kind of outgrow a small niche?
Are you basically saying any niche you
can blow up?
>> You know, I just have so much
confirmation bias that has like informed
me of that belief where like there's
been so many niches where they're like,
"There's no way I can make a knitting
channel go viral. There's no way I can
make an astrophotography channel go
viral. there's no way I can make a
horiculture niche go viral. And we have
just seen those examples like time and
time again where like when you do go
broader, when you do look for those
bigger ideas, you can reach more people.
So I yeah, I do think there's there's a
limit to how many views you can get in
those niches, but like you know an
example of I have a friend who does like
reviews on like website builders and
just like covers different like like Wix
versus Squarespace, all these things.
And it's like, well, that's that's a
pretty small niche in itself, but if you
have 100,000 viewers watching those
pieces of content, those are really high
value viewers, you know? So, I think
there is a limit to how far niches can
go. But in theory, you know, I I just
haven't seen an example yet where I look
at a niche and I'm like, so long as
there's some level of interest there.
Like, sure, if you're like, my niche is
Irish guys who live in Austin, Texas,
and like pickle ball only, it's like,
oh, okay, well, you just have Patty,
that's that's your only viewer. But I
think generally speaking, so long as
there's some level of interest in the
thing you're doing, you know, whether it
be golf, like I remember when people
said like golf doesn't work on YouTube.
Golf's huge on YouTube now. It's like
one of the biggest like niches on
YouTube right now.
>> The reality is is I think anybody out
there, you know, the bigger the TAM, the
better I feel like. But it's also like
how do they find that sweet spot with a
big TAM, but it's kind of underexposed
and not a lot of people are building
there. So how do you look at TAM in
general? like how do people go out there
and find kind of these markets where
hopefully they're medium to big size and
like little competition like how do you
find out what the volume is and the
competition is from a TAM perspective?
>> Well, I think that the first thing is at
least for me is
we have to understand like the
intersection between our skill, what
we're good at and what there's demand
for before even getting to the TAM
question because like I do sometimes see
people just chasing these niches where
they're like, "Oh, this goes really
viral. Minecraft goes really viral.
Roblox goes really viral or this is the
latest viral thing in business or or
whatever it might be. I always like to
think of it as like these two circles,
you know, intersecting and it's like you
have your passions, your skills, your
maybe your competitive advantages as a
person, what you're you're best at and
then you have what is in demand on
YouTube right now or what you know do
you think there is going to be demand
for? That intersection is usually where
I like to to live. Like where is that
intersection? To me though, it's like
one of the best ways to find evidence of
if there is something working is just
are there small channels in a niche that
are overperforming. So so much of my
career has just been built on studying
how do small channels grow? Like
everyone's like, "Oh, how does how does
Mr. Beast grow?" You can learn a lot
from Mr. Beast. I learn a lot from this
tiny channel with a 100 subscribers that
just posted a video that got 3,000
views. It's like that to me is like it's
the equivalent of if you're like a a VC
fund seeing a company that is tiny and
you know but it's grown from like 10k a
month in revenue to 30k a month in
revenue in a month and it's like oh okay
that's kind of interesting. So I look at
I look for really small channels that
are starting to see some traction and I
start to sort of reverse engineer like
is there something about their niche? Is
there something about their execution?
Like why is that working?
>> Yeah. I think for people out there too
we have a lot of creators but also
operators. What you're basically saying,
ironically, it's the name of your
company is outliers where if the base
average is 100 views and it gets 3,000,
it's basically a 30x outlier. So, you
want to look for those ones that kind of
get disproportionately more views. What
are like the tools that you're using?
We're we're big one of 10 guys. What do
you use to kind of see those outliers?
>> I think one of 10 view stats, Vid IQ,
like the tool doesn't matter that much.
It's just like so long as it shows you
videos on YouTube and it shows you the
average score. So, like average views of
the channel and then the outlier score.
So the outlier score being 30x average
views or 50x average views
>> makes a lot of sense. Yeah. Like for us
out there guys to give you guys more
context like from a guest perspective,
we'd like to, you know, we would look at
you on other channels and are you an
outlier? Are you not? Patty is an
outlier. He's got that he's got that
sauce. So definitely I think if anybody
is going to go invest in any idea, any
person, any guest, they should see how
those ideas, concepts, or people have
performed on other channels.
>> But you want to know something funny?
>> What? That's how I found you, too.
>> You serious?
>> I saw you flash up on one of my tools
and I was like, "Oh [__] this guy's
started a podcast.
>> I think one of your first guests got
like maybe 50 60,000 views, right? Then
you had Samir on. It did well." And I
was like, "You're overperforming." Like,
you're overperforming your expectation.
If I looked How many subscribers you on
right now?
>> Probably by the time this comes out, I'd
say 60,000 subscribers.
>> 60,000 subscribers. So, if I looked at a
60,000 subscriber channel, I would sort
of assume the viewership would be like 5
to 10,000 views.
>> We smashing over that. And you're
probably averaging
>> combined video and audio 100,000.
>> 100,000. So it's like you're an outlier.
So speaking back to that like idea like
you know you saw me you saw that on
other podcasts I've been on it's
overperformed their channels average. I
saw that you were overperforming you
know other podcasts as well.
>> Interesting. Really quick just to do the
math because I know that you're like
very formulaic in nature. How do you
look at subscribers versus average views
and kind of like the benchmark? I mean
it seems as though you just benchmarked
60,000 subs to 10,000 views. So, are you
saying what, like 5 10% of subs should
be viewing? Like what are those what's
that ratio that you're looking at?
>> So, what's interesting is like
subscribers in 2026 to be honest, I
don't really care about kind of dead.
They're a little bit of a vanity metric.
And look, it's still like the score.
It's still what people used to keep
score. Like, you know, Mr. Beast doesn't
go, "Oh, I just hit 150 million views on
average video. Next milestone." It's
like, I just hit 500K subscribers or 500
million subscribers. So, it's still this
the thing that keeps score, but it's not
it's not overly important from an
algorithmic perspective. I just use it
as like a rough like idea. If a
channel's like 50 60,000 subscribers,
where would I in my mind generally think
the viewership would be? Probably like
you you typically see maybe 20% of their
subscriber count would be quite normal.
But if you're overperforming, it's very
common to see a channel that's like, you
know, way above that. When I had my when
I did my channel, I had 200 300,000
subscribers and I was hitting a million
2 million views every episode on my
channel and it was like overperformed
that subscriber count.
>> More views and subs. That's a winner.
Completely agree there. Guys, this
episode is sponsored by Ketone IQ. I
often sit down in this chair for over 3
hours and stay super dialed with
ketones. It's a completely different
category of fuel for your brain. [music]
Clean, sustained, and no crash. I take a
shot before recording, before [music]
deep work, and any session that I need
to be sharp. Head to ketone.com/open
residency for 30% off your first
subscription and a free gift with your
second [music] shipment. That's
ke.com/open
residency. Guys, this is something that
I use every [music] single day,
non-negotiable. Give it a try.
I want to keep diving into principles
and framers. We've talked a lot about
you can win in a niche. What are ways to
kind of look at TAMs and kind of find
outliers? We're gonna get way more into
the outliers. I love this CCN framework
that you talk about. We're going to pop
up right here at Visual on that, too.
Why don't you kind of walk us through
the three types of viewers and how
people should approach kind of
positioning and packaging their videos?
>> Yeah, I came up with this framework
probably four years, four or five years
ago, and it's one of those moments where
it's so simple, but then I was like, oh,
this actually sums up content as a whole
and content strategy as a whole. So the
idea here is most channels and I think
this goes for different platforms as
well whether it's Instagram, Tik Tok,
you know, whatever. You have these three
three main groups of viewers. Your core
viewers are the people that basically
are ride or die, like the 10,000 true
fans. These are the people who like will
kind of tune in no matter what for you.
If you're starting out, you probably
don't have much of a core. If you're at
zero, like obviously you don't have a
core. But even for you right now on the
podcast, you probably know that there's
like out of the 100,000 viewers you're
getting across the episodes, it's
probably like three, four, 5,000 people
that are like, I'll watch every episode.
This is great. I'm there. And that's
your core. And they're very valuable.
But that's the core. The casual are the
people who dip in and dip out. They
maybe watch one in every three, one in
every four videos or episodes. And
they're very valuable because if you can
capture more of them, you can start to
turn them into core viewers. But that's
your casual audience. And then you have
new viewers. New viewers are all the
potential viewers you could reach every
time you upload. Now, this can be
overwhelming because if you think about
it, like, you know, there are over a
billion viewers on YouTube. So, that can
be like overwhelming. Well, could I
reach a billion views? No. But in your
niche, you know, with the idea of what
your TAM might be, like how many viewers
do you think there is? So, for like a
business operator podcast, there's
probably like 500K to a million viewers
out there. So, you're like, "Well,
there's all these new viewers I'm still
not reaching with my videos." And the
idea of the core, casual, new viewer
framework, the CCN framework, is you
want videos that your core viewer can
watch and enjoy, your casual viewer can
watch and enjoy, and a new viewer can
watch and enjoy.
>> So, hit all three.
>> Hit all three. And it sounds so basic,
but it actually starts to make it really
difficult cuz if you think about it, the
kind of idea that your core wants, the
kind of videos your core wants the most,
might be very different to the videos
that attract new viewers. and vice
versa, the videos that maybe attract the
most new viewers, that might completely
alienate the core. So, so many mistakes
in YouTube strategy come from tailoring
too much to the core and just making
these videos that are just like super
niche. Like if you I always like to say
like, you know, I think it was was it
Henry Ford that said if I asked people
what they wanted, they they would have
said a faster horse, you know, instead
of a car. I think about YouTube, it's
like if you ask your comment section
what they want, they'll just say more of
the old thing you used to do that no
longer works because they're like, I
missed that. Do that again. And it's
like you're not a good strategist. You
just want what you know you want to
watch as a as a viewer. So I don't
really listen to my comment section that
much. I'll pay attention but like you
know looking at the core can really sort
of you know make you focus too much on
small narrow topics. Even think about
the creators you like the most. Like you
know let's just say someone like a
Hermosi who's like a huge business
creator. Like I think if me or you as as
people who own companies wanted herozi
to make a video we tell him the video we
want him to make he'd be like okay I
could make that. it's going to get
10,000 viewers because there's very few
people at your level that want to watch
that video, right? So, I think the core
is is a really hard one to hit, but it's
super important. And then on the flip
side, you know, your new new viewers,
like I see these channels all the time
that just like they're you can tell
they're just chasing these new viewers.
They're like, "Oh, come over here. Come
over here." And they're trying to grab
them. They're like, "Come over here.
Grab I'm gonna grab you here with this
idea. I'm going to grab you with this
idea." And there's no like throughine.
There's no reason to keep watching the
channel. It's just like you're just
making whatever goes viral in a given
moment. you're just trying to attract
new viewers. So to me, the best videos
on YouTube, they can be watched by
people who have watched every video on
your channel, that have watched a couple
videos on your channel, and have never
watched your channel before. And I like
to use that framework to to help with
that.
>> Yeah. I think for people out there
listening is obviously you need some
sort of kind of through line that kind
of filters in all three of those
buckets. For us, it's business. And to
hit the new, like you really have to
basically take a swing and kind of try
something completely new. Like for us,
you know, Dave Gutman, who's a big
hospitality guy in Miami, like he was a
kind of different type of episode. We
had had on basically only operators and
creators, and we brought on this kind of
hospitality guy, but it was through the
lens of business. So, you had the core
people, they wanted to hear about
business. The casual people, maybe
they've been to Miami, and then the new
people, maybe it's hospitality people.
So, I think you need to you have to be
big and bold. You have to try new things
to hit the new audience, or else you're
going to stay kind of stagnant and not
grow and stick with the core. Exactly.
And I love this example that we have
here from one of our previous clients,
Jesser, who is I think the biggest one
of the biggest sports channels in the
world. Right now,
>> guys, if you're on audio, make sure you
get on video right now because we're
popping up right now a great example
that you can walk through. Yeah. Why
don't you walk us through right now how
and why it hits these different three.
>> So, this this is a great example. I I
love using this because these three
videos were all posted within the same
month on the same channel, right? So,
this was these were all posted on a big
channel. They were all like, you know,
thought out, planned. They had their own
thumbnail, all these different things,
right? You see on the far left, core,
official reveal of my new YouTube
studio, full tour. So, if you don't know
who that is, why do you give a [__]
about that video? Like, official reveal
of your new, you know, who likes that
video? Like, YouTube nerds, like
production nerds, like we're like, "Oh,
that's cool. Let's watch that." But
really, the only people that would watch
that is his core audience, 400,000
people. So, it's actually a pretty easy
way to see what what is your core
audience. there's probably 400,000
people cuz you made a video that's not
very interesting and only 400,000 people
watch.
>> That's almost like a day in the life
type thing like where it's very kind of
intimate and specific to the one person.
>> And there is still sometimes a value to
trying those videos. But if you're
trying to grow a channel, if you're
trying to build the biggest possible
audience, they do hold you back.
>> You look at the right core casual,
right? Insane make the shot I'll buy you
anything challenge. Why do I think
that's core casual? Well, it's core
because again the core just like the
creator, they like Jer. It's casual
because most of his casual viewers have
watched previous videos like this on his
channel. Like it's it's a decent idea.
There's some level of stakes, but it's
kind of basic. There's nothing that
special or unique about that idea. And
if you look at the the one on the far
right here, core casual new.
>> I'm interested.
>> Going to five NBA games in 50 hours.
It's difficult. It's a challenge. It
feels he's kind of like signaling effort
to you. Like we all have this effort
bias as humans that if we see someone
doing something that feels high effort,
we look at it and go, "Oh, wow." Like
that's impressive. like how did he do
that or I want to see that. So going to
five NBA games in 50 hours 14 million
views and I think it's a great beautiful
example of these things. His core
audience is 400,000 viewers. So that
video got 4,000 views. His casual is
maybe closer to a million at least at
the time. So you know that one got just
under a million views. And then the new
viewer well the TAM for basketball on
YouTube might be like 10 to 20 million
views and he got 14 million views on
that video. Again, three videos, one
video has just dramatically bigger
outcome because it is reaching to new
viewers as well. I use Whisper Flow for
hours every single day. [music] I think
way faster than I type. I speak about
220 words a minute and type only 45.
Whisper Flow closes that gap. It's a
voiceto text tool that works anywhere on
your computer or phone. You talk and
clean formatted text shows up wherever
your cursor is. All right, let me show
you. I'm going to answer a real email
right now without typing. You can see
here Taigga is asking for feedback on
our intro video for the next episode.
Watch how I respond. If you could just
make a few changes. Uh make the red a
little bit brighter, the typography a
little bit smaller. Uh for the music, if
you can just give me [music] some other
options and that first photo, some more
options as well. Uh please give me
[music] three options for each and uh
make sure you send it to me by end of
the day Friday. Thanks.
So, as you can tell, the text is way
[music] cleaner. I kind of speak in half
sentences and sometimes mumble on. This
makes it very clean, formatted
perfectly, and avoids all the small
mistakes. This is a product that I
cannot live without. I promise you that
you will love it. If you guys want to
get one month free of Whisper Flow Pro,
click the link below and use code open
residency.
>> Where do you see people going wrong with
this kind of CCN network? Like what are
those big mistakes that people are
making? I would say one big mistake is
not understanding the importance of a
throughine and actually just in general
especially when I talk to actually
entrepreneurs this is really interesting
like I think entrepreneurs generally
have like a ton of interests and they
try to do a ton of different things and
what they'll do that's wrong in my
opinion when it comes to this framework
and just ideation in general is they'll
they assume that there's too much
overlap or there's more overlap than
actually exists between different
topics.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. So, I always like to think of
this thing where like actually speaking
of Red Bull, our client Red Bull, when I
started working at Red Bull in 2022 on
their channel, they had like, you know,
parkour, the snowboarding athlete, you
know, this rock climbing, then F1 and
then soccer, and then all these
different things. And it's like, great,
okay, but who are the people who
actually like all these different sports
at the same time and care about all
these different sports at the same time
and all these different athletes? cuz I
was just like, you know, I I think at
the time, like she's much bigger now,
but Eileen Goo, who's like the skater or
something, um I remember going, "Who's
Een Goo?" And they're like, "You don't
know who Eing Goo is?" And I'm like,
"No." And it's like, I think very few
people in the world know who all these
people are and care about all these
people. And the people that do, they
work for Rebel, right? They're like,
"You." So, I love I love to think of
that idea of like there isn't that much
overlap between topics. Like even video
games, right? If I said like Battlefield
and Call of Duty, they're both first
person shooters. They're both very
popular, like huge AAA games, right? The
overlap between those two games, 20% in
my opinion, if I had to guess right now,
like 20% of people that play Call of
Duty regularly also play Battlefield
regularly. So, you'll see these channels
and they're like, "Oh, I'm a gaming
channel. I do first-person shooter
content." And I'm like, "Okay, let's
see. Oh, I do Counter-Strike, I do
Battlefield, and I do Call of Duty."
It's like, bro, like these are like
completely different things. And then
you can take the ex exact same thing
into like, you know, a business channel
or like, you know, if if you're like a
health channel. Let's just say you're a
health and fitness channel. It's like,
well, there's a big difference between
bodybuilding and yoga and stretching.
And these are all different niches with
different audience profiles. And people
are so dialed in on what they like that
you can't jump around as much as you
think.
>> Yeah. I think any of the kind of new
categories need to be somewhat adjacent.
You don't want these like crazy
contrasts. And I also feel like it's
like for us it's a maniacal focus on
looking through a business lens and like
I obviously have other passions but I
know that we need a certain amount of
kind of escape velocity where I can
start going deep with like health and
wellness type people or you know in a
perfect world like Joe Rogan can bring
on MMA and comedy like I love all that
random stuff but you just you have to
stay super deep and narrow and then
incrementally bring on more categories.
Do you agree with that?
>> I 100% agree with that. And the thing is
it it kind of goes back to our TAM
discussion which is like there are
sometimes you you're attracted to like
going after the biggest broadest thing
but that is the most competitive right
you can't go that way. So what I mean by
that is you can't really start broad and
go narrow. Just doesn't really work. You
can start narrow and just gradually
expand and grow outwards and grow
outwards and grow outwards. Like I think
nearly every channel I've ever worked on
that has grown to become a massive
channel. They've started in something
very small and then they've just
expanded expanded expanded. So Forest
Galante is right now the most viewed
wildlife channel on YouTube and he's our
client. We signed him at 20 20 to 30,000
views a video back in 2023. We realized
that his kind of niche within a niche,
so wildlife is a niche, right? But his
niche within a niche is like extinct
animals. So back then most of our videos
most of our topics were around extinct
animals. They were around like you know
lizards, dangerous animals, things that
went extinct like the pylo scenes which
are like the Tasmanian tiger or
something. And if you look at the
channel now it's like we're doing
private tours of big zoos. We're doing
like videos with big cats. We're getting
millions of views per video. But like we
didn't start like that. We expanded out
over time.
>> Deep and narrow start there. I mean we
started with ecom operators. Then we
kind of brought in CPG operators and now
we're expanding to operators in business
and kind of different categories. So I
completely agree. I want to kind of
from a pattern recognition perspective
let the audience know like what are
those true you know we keep talking
about views. What are those true kind of
hallmarks and things that need to be
consistent for these videos to get 1,
five, 10 million views? Like what are
those key things that you kind of look
for there?
>> So yeah, CCM fit. They have CCM fit. I
always like to think that they can be
understood in a second. So, a really
interesting thing about us as humans is
is I think when we're actually making
something, we assume that people are
going to give it a lot more
consideration than they do. I'm sure you
see that all the time in, you know,
e-commerce and and whatnot. It's like
you think people are going to look at it
and be like, "Oh, yeah. I see the way he
made that label like that. That's going
to make me buy." Whereas, it's really
usually much more impulsive than that.
And I always invite people if you have
like, you know, a partner or just a
friend and they're watching YouTube, pay
attention. See how they're watching
YouTube, right? Let's just say, you
know, you're with your friend and
they're watching YouTube on a TV.
They're just they're just they're
scrolling like this through videos.
They're clicking clicking clicking.
Things are getting a second of time.
They're getting a second. That's it.
They're getting a second. And on your
phone, you're scrolling by videos like
this, right? And yet when we're making a
video, an idea, we're like, you know,
sometimes I'll have people come up to me
in the street. You know, I very rarely,
but someone will get recognized and then
someone's like, "Oh my god, I've got a
crazy viral idea I want to pitch to
you." And I'm like, "Okay." And then
they go, "So what's going to happen is
it's going to be like this and then this
person's going to come in and we're" and
I'm like, "Dude, can you explain that
again?" And then they explain it again.
I'm like, "You've taken like 30 or 40
seconds to explain what this video is."
Every video I've worked on that's had 10
million views. I've even worked on
videos with over 100 million views, you
can always just say them in one second
and people are like, I get it. I get it
right away. So, I always like to think
the hallmark, one of the biggest
hallmarks of viral ideas is like, can it
pass the glance test? Can someone just
look at it and be like, oh, I get that.
I want to watch that. And a big problem
new creators make, a big problem
entrepreneurs make on YouTube is they
just make these very complicated titles,
too long, too many things happening. And
I'm like, if you can't put your idea
into a sentence that is just one line
that I can understand, a log line, it's
not a good idea. I don't care. They're
like, it's the best video idea ever. I
just need a way to package it. I'm like,
well, then it's not a good idea. It's
just it's just a random thought. So
>> simple, not complex words. You can't do
anything. You just need to increase the
absor absorption rate. Anybody quick
glance can see it real quick and
understand and know where you're going
to go. So CCN I would just say
simplicity is another big one. What else
you have here?
>> I would say big thing for me is like
universal appeal. So, it kind of goes a
bit back to the core casual noob, but
basically when I was making videos on my
channel, I went into the niche and it
was, you know, YouTube education content
and lots of great creators in YouTube
education space, but it was all like,
you know, five packaging tips or 10 ways
to grow a YouTube channel in 2018, you
know, this sort of stuff. And it was
getting 5 10 15,000 views a video. I
went in and I said, I think I can get a
million views a video in this space,
which no one was doing. And I went in
and, you know, flash forward five or six
years of doing that, I was doing a
million views an episode in that space.
And what I used was this idea that like
I want to make videos that are
interesting to the biggest YouTuber in
the world and my mother at the same
time. And I wanted to make ideas that
like, you know, my mother would watch
and be like, "This is really
interesting." Biggest YouTuber in the
world be like, "This is really
interesting. I'm still getting stuff."
And if you ever go back, I I think this
is interesting. You go back and watch
like kids movies, the best kids movies,
you watch them as a kid, they were
great. You're like, "This is amazing."
You watch them as an adult and you're
like, "This is still great. This is even
better than I thought. It's layered and
there's like multiple things for every
every person." So, I think a big thing I
look for as well is just that universal
appeal. Like this can be watched by a
large number of people, you know, and
not be alienating. Like there's this
little example I give all the time,
which is so small, but like I have this
friend in Dallas. He had, you know, big
YouTube channel over a million
subscribers. I was reviewing one of his
videos with him and he introduced his in
the video he he just sort of like had
this character, let's just call, let's
say her name was like Katie, right? And
Katie came in and and he's like, "Okay,
today Katie, you're going to go do
this." And she's like, "Okay." And she
goes and starts doing it. And then flash
forward like 5 minutes later, he goes,
"Katie, come over here." And Katie comes
over and he kisses her. And I'm like,
"What? They're romantically involved? I
didn't know that. Right. And I sat on
the call. I'm like, "What's this?" And
he goes, "That's my girlfriend." And I'm
like, "Well, I didn't know it was your
girlfriend and you just kissed her in
the video." And he's like, "Oh, my
audience knows." He's like, "Okay, your
audience that watches you know, but do
the new viewers know?" And now they feel
in it? And he's like, "Oh, so then
should I like set it up every video and
be like, "She's my girlfriend?" And I'm
like, "No, because then that also is
annoying to the core viewers cuz then
they're having to be constantly
reintroduced. So, how do you do it?"
Well, instead of being like, "Hey
everyone, this is my girlfriend, Katie."
You might say something like, "Katie,
look, I know you're my girlfriend, but
can you go do this really quickly?" Now,
you've sewn that seed into the viewer's
head that they know, "Oh, that's his
girlfriend." So, when you kiss her
later, it doesn't feel like, "Why did he
do that?" That's that's, you know, a
kind of a gap or a plot hole. And I
think that comes back to the same
principle of making videos that as many
people can watch without feeling like
they're losing something or missing
something. I always hate when people
say, "You probably saw my last video."
No, I didn't. I didn't watch your last
video, you know. Oh. Oh, like as we
discussed last week. What you mean
discussed last week? This is the first
time I've been here. So, I always like
look at my video and put it through the
lens of can someone who has never
watched me before watch this video and
enjoy it.
>> I think the big takeaway here is all
roads lead to CCN. You have to look, you
have to filter through that in every
single level, title, thumbnail, the
actual core of the video to make sure
everybody has full context and just get
creative like how how you just mentioned
100%.
>> Any other big ones do you think there
that we need to touch on?
So, another one that I see which is, you
know, we we're going to talk more about
packaging as we go through the episode
together, but I think when I look at
these videos that have 10, 50, 100
million views, they always pose a
question that you have to click to
answer. So, not only are like from a
pure like objective point of view,
they're appealing to lots of people.
They've got universal appeal. They they
the CCNA, all this stuff, they put
something in front of you that you look
at and you say, I need to click this to
get the answer, right? So, going to five
NBA games in 50 hours, it's like, I need
to click this to see if he actually did
it. Like, what games did he go to? Like,
did he like how did he get there? How is
this even possible? So, the best videos
on YouTube, I think they create this
like dynamic where like you're almost
feeling like you're having to like
unpause.
Like you're having to click unpause to
watch it. And I always like to say that
like, you know, if you put an idea in
front of someone like and they're just
about to go do something really
important, is it good enough where
they're like, I need to watch this
first.
>> Curiosity gap is the big thing there.
Just open it up and make people clip in.
>> So, I feel like a lot of people get
confused between like novel ideas and
original ideas. How do you look at just
ideas in general and how do you kind of
like ideulate all of these ideas?
>> There's three main sources of great
YouTube ideas in my opinion. You have
internal, external, and innovation.
Internal ideas are ideas that have like
worked for you previously. And it's it's
so funny like you know quite often,
look, we're really good at what we do,
but quite often people expect us to kind
of like come in with some like crazy
fresh unique idea that's never been done
before. One of the first things we do
when we work on a channel is we go
through and we look at what are videos
they have done in the past that have
worked well. Can we put a twist on this?
Can we adapt it? Can we improve it? Can
we do something different with this
idea? And so often it is just like oh do
that again. And they're like but but but
my viewers they they would already have
seen that. It's like content moves fast.
Like people have forgot about it. Do it
again. Right? I used to run one of the
biggest travel pages on Instagram for
Ireland. It was called Discovering
Ireland. And what I noticed really
quickly is I would just basically have
five or six photos that I would post
every year, the same photos. And like at
the time I was like, I can't post this.
My my followers have already seen that
photo of the beautiful cliffs. It's like
they they want to see it again, right?
So internal ideas to me are all about
like what has performed well for you in
the past. Is there ways you can do it
again? Can you repeat it? Can you double
down? And I think what's interesting in
2026 is YouTube strategy has become more
common. When I started this, like
YouTube strategy wasn't even a thing.
You should a YouTube strategist wasn't a
thing. I would tell people I'm YouTube
strategist. They'd be like, "What?
What's that?" And I was being paid $50
an hour. Like it was just not a skill
that was valued or anyone knew about.
But nowadays, it's so common place that
like people know what outlier ideation
is or what like doubling down is. So if
you make an idea that does well, someone
else is going to copy that pretty
quickly. I want to be the own person, my
own person to copy myself. I want to
like double down quick. So those are
internal ideas. External ideas are
basically this idea of outlaw ideation.
So what are ideas that have
overperformed for other channels in my
niche and in adjacent niches. So I will
use tools like we mentioned earlier,
these outlier tools, one of 10, view
stats, Vid IQ, they all they all all do
these different things and I will go
through and I will look for ideas that
have overperformed the channel average
usually by three or 4x. So at least 3x
the channel's average. So if a you know
channel is doing like 100,000 views a
video, if they have a video that gets 3
400,000 views, that's interesting to me.
There's something about that whether
they meant it or not, they stumbled
across something that worked. So me as a
creator, I want to go in and figure out
like is there a way I can adapt that? So
>> how does your brain kind of filter all
these? One of them is obviously the
topic. I would say title is one,
thumbnail is one. Like what are the big
things that you're looking for to find
those kind of similarities that you
could bring to your videos? I would say
usually when I'm using Outlaw radiation
and you you do see a video that has 3
400,000 views, it's kind of rarely
something about the editing or the
intro. Not the retention isn't really
important. It is, but it is usually just
like the title, the thumbnail, just
something about that. Whether it's like
how they package it different to their
other videos. Like quite often I'll look
at it and say I won't just look at the
video that got 400,000 views. I'll look
at the videos that got 100,000 views and
say what is different about these
videos? Like is there did they try
different formats? Did they try a
different style? Did they try a
different title? And really what I'm
doing with with external ideation is I'm
not just looking at what worked and
copying it. I'm looking at what worked.
I'm taking lots of them. Almost like
imagine you just have this big pile of
ideas that worked in other niches. So if
I'm a golf channel, what am I looking
at? I'm looking at every other golf
channel in the last, let's say, 365
days. What are the videos that have
three or 4x the average views on their
channel? I'm taking all those ideas. I'm
putting them in my brain. Then I'm
saying, well, what's adjacent to golf?
What are other hobbies or niches that
are kind of similar to golf? I'm going
to say fishing. It seems very different,
but like technically it's enjoyed by a
very similar demographic to golf. You
know, it involves a lot of equipment
like rods and you got your clubs. It's a
pursuit. It's a hobby. It's a pastime.
Okay. I'm also going to look at all the
fishing channels. What were outliers for
fishing channels? Oh, someone made a
video where they, you know, fished with
wooden fishing rods. Maybe I play around
of golf with wooden golf clubs, right?
Like there's, you know, definitely ways
you can take adjacent niches and combine
them. What I'm doing there is I'm taking
all my internal ideas, all the ideas
that work for us, all the ideas that
have worked for other people and other
niches similar to mine, and I'm kind of
putting them all together like they're
at the top of this funnel, which we can
probably visualize in some way, and just
thinking like, okay, let's put those all
into my brainstorming funnel. And then
the last one is innovation. That's the
one that you you really started this
question with, which is like this idea
of novel, new, completely fresh, and
different. I'm going to make a somewhat
controversial statement, which is I
think for a lot of small creators at the
start, coming up with completely fresh
new ideas is quite challenging and you
should do it, but it should probably be
something that's like a percentage of
your strategy. Maybe it's like 20% of
your videos are, you know, things that
you're trying that have never been done
before. And, you know, how do you come
up with those ideas? I mean, that's the
hardest thing to actually sort of create
a system around. It's like what has
never been done before? Something I I
like to do is like, what if I combined
two different things to create something
new? That's how I created my channel. No
one was doing video essay breakdowns on
YouTube channels before I did in 2016
was when I posted my first one. I saw
people doing video essay breakdowns on
Hollywood. I saw people doing like
detailed business sort of whiteboard
videos about business and I said, "What
if I did that for YouTube?"
>> Just took the format and just brought it
to your topic.
>> Yeah. I blended them together to create
something new. So innov innovation is
still like a powerful like tactic with
this with this funnel. But the idea for
me is I think a lot of smaller creators
and you know even like entrepreneurs and
people that come into this space every
idea they make is just like I have no
evidence this is going to work. I just
think it's cool and I'll make it. And if
you're goal is to make YouTube a fun
hobby. That's great. But if your goal is
to grow the biggest channel on YouTube
which is my goal in every niche I'm in.
If I work with a finance channel, which
we have, I say I want to build this to
be the biggest finance channel in the
world. If I work with a wildlife
channel, biggest wildlife channel in the
world, that is my goal with every every
niche, there's got to be like a fair
amount of emphasis put on like data,
what's working, what's worked for us,
what's worked for other people.
>> Guys, this podcast is not for hobbyists
here. We're here to to go deep. So,
completely agree with you there. So I
think taking a step back again, I think
there's a lot of operators on here that
their YouTube is a corporate dumping
ground and we want to get them kind of
on the right track. So looking at kind
of those three prongs, if you have
nothing, start external, see what's
working, test some stuff on your side.
Once you have x amount of videos, then
maybe look inward internal, use what's
working, kind of reiterate, and then
once you have like a little bit of
scale, that's when you can start
innovating and kind of taking new shots
on that.
>> That's beautifully put. Yeah. like spot
on because
>> if you start with that like what
actually happens is like you know
because when I when I say the word
internal to someone they're like well I
have no videos that have worked yet.
>> At the same time you know on that point
I do sometimes think like if you're
averaging a,000 views a video and you
have a video with 5,000 views still data
it's still an overperformer. It might
seem small but it's still an
overperformer but like at the start you
might not have that. So yeah, it is just
a case of like let me go and find if I
was just starting a completely new
channel in any niche, you know, let's
just say it's health and wellness, let's
just say it's beverages, let's just say
it's like finance, website builders.
First thing I'm doing from scratch is I
am going I'm using these tools. I'm
finding every single outlier in this
niche and adjacent niches over the last
two years, maybe there's like a thousand
and I'm taking them and I'm saying, what
is my spin on that? What is my spin on
that? What is my twist on that on each
one of them?
>> Yeah, for people out there listening,
the best YouTube pages are doing this.
Like it's so funny, man, cuz you just
see I remember we actually used one of
the titles for it. It was like someone I
think it was maybe hormonia or my first
million. They talked about like the gold
rush of something. It was an outlier. It
performed well and then you start seeing
all these kind of business channels that
are ahead and understand YouTube using
gold rush is it has its time. It does
well and then it's kind of on to the
next one. So, it's really about finding
it and then just squeezing as much juice
out of it while the juice is still good
and then maybe you revisit it years down
the line.
>> Yeah. And the thing about doing it and
this is this is why I love that you said
that and I think this is why at a
certain point it just becomes around
surrounding yourself with with like
outliers just like if I don't know if
you want to be like really fit like you
surround yourself with like loads of
guys that have 10% body fat and you're
like okay I'm going to start maybe I'm
going to skip that burger. I'm going to
start dieting and you know trying to get
better. I think with YouTube, if you're
just surrounding yourself with videos,
like I I like to think of my brain as
just like I am just putting things
through my eyes all the time that have
worked for other people to try to like
then when I have a problem or when I
have an idea I need to come up with,
think about, oh, that went viral for
that channel. I can pull brain videos
from my brain that were like viral on a
channel 6 years ago and be like that
could work for this channel or that
could work for this thing. And it comes
from surrounding yourself. And one idea
I I really like which we came up with
with a client that I used to work with,
Noah Kagan. I'm not sure if you know
Noah before.
>> I know. Crazy Noah in Austin.
>> Yeah, absolutely. Legend. But I remember
I came into his channel. He was doing
like maybe like 5 or 10,000 views a
video at the time. And I worked with his
creative director, a guy named Jeremy, a
great guy.
>> And the sort of goal for them was
simple. It was like, we want to build
bigger videos. We want to go more viral.
So they came up with this idea with us
which was like asking millionaires how
to make a million dollars. Now if you
look on YouTube right now, that is like
everywhere, right? There's like a
million people doing it. But what's
interesting, you might have even seen
this thumbnail. I'm sure we can show
examples of this, but this like concept
of like someone with their hands
outstretched, someone answering a door,
and then some yellow text in the middle.
It's like, "How did you get rich?" or
whatever. That actually came from from
me and from us, from my team.
>> Wow.
>> Back in 200 I think 21.
And
>> I've seen videos of him like knocking on
door people's doors in just big houses
and being like, "How'd you get rich?"
>> Exactly. And what happened was was
interesting is this idea was in front of
us. We were thinking about it and I was
just like, "Oh, there was a video that
went viral a cooking video that went
viral three years ago which was titled
asking Canadians to cook them dinner in
their kitchen." And it was a guy who
went and knocked on doors and he had
this in the thumbnail he had this piece
of text which said, "Can I cook in your
kitchen?" And it had someone answering
the door kind of like shocked, right?
That got like 9 million views at the
time in on a very small channel. I saw
it because I've been tracking videos for
decades, right? So, I saw it and I was
like, "Huh, someday I'm going to use
that." Sitting there with Noah, he's
averaging 5 to 10,000 views a video with
his team. And it's like this this video,
which is like asking millionaires how to
make a million dollars. We're going to
go knock on people's doors and ask them
how they got rich. And I'm like, "Oh my
god, I've got the thumb concept." Like,
let's put Noah here with his hands
outstretched. Let's put a backwards cap
on him. If you actually go look, we can
show the references. I'll send them to
you afterwards. But the the actual
reference from the the Canadian cooking
channel had like a backwards cap on and
he's asking like this. Put text in the
middle. put the person there, have the
person like sort of shocked and staring
right at him, make it not too posed.
Let's make that thumbnail. That video
got 5 million views and created one of
the biggest like trends in the whole
business space on YouTube. And it was
just from like combining multiple things
together. And the actual title itself,
right, Hermosi had made a title which
was something like I asked a billionaire
how to make a billion dollars. So when
we were making the title, we were like,
you know, asking millionaires how to get
rich. I knocked on millionaires doors to
ask them how to make more money. H let's
let's think about this. I asked them I
asked millionaires how to make a million
dollars. So that kind of came from that
Hermoszi title, right? So you see how
like you're almost like Frankensteining
like this thumbnail idea from this video
and this title from this video and
you're combining these all together to
try to get like something new and fresh
and then the actual concept for the
video kind of came from like Daniel Mack
like asking supercar owners how they got
rich and you know you know what do you
do for a living that kind of stuff. So
you've kind of got this idea where
you're taking short form a short form
idea and making it long form. You're
taking a title from Hermosi here and
adapting it. You're taking a thumbnail
concept from this random Canadian
cooking channel and you're combining all
together to get something that got five
million views and became like the most
viral business video of 2022.
>> That's insane the amount of touch points
that lead up to one video. I mean,
people just see the end concept and they
don't know kind of what goes into it.
Guys, I love the guys at one of 10.
We're going to pop down below some like
link or coupon code or something for
them. We've been using them since the
beginning and yeah, I just think it's
put a folder all the outliers and mix
and match topics, formats, styles,
anything and everything and just create
your kind of own new thing. I want to
get into just ideation in general kind
of like your ideation system. How many
ideas are you doing per video and is
there any like principles or frameworks
that you could share? Yeah, I think the
way I think about it and I got this from
Steve Jobs which is not that he told me
personally which is
110 one. So really when you think about
it you start you have zero. So you start
at zero then you decide well like
roughly what are the guiding principles
of what I want to make videos around. So
at that point like you start to think
about like well what's a core casual new
viewer for for my channel? What are the
videos that serve me the most? what are
the videos that like I think are going
to bring in the most correct viewers for
my channel. It's not always about total
viewers. It's also about like, you know,
I want to make sure I get the right
viewers for my channel. So, you kind of
start to inform yourself a little bit
about like what sort of viewers you're
looking for. Then you think about this
framework which I like to use which is
the 80% strategy rule. And it's not the
paro principle. It's very different.
It's this idea that the best channels
they are looking for videos that have
80% overlap with each other. So, I
talked about this earlier, but overlap
is one of those things that people
really overestimate. They think there's
more overlap between things than there
actually is. So, the 80% strategy rule
is basically saying we need to look for
videos that have 80% overlap with each
other, topics that have 80% overlap with
each other, and we should do that 80% of
the time. So, we have this kind of 20%
of the time where we can try something
different, try something new. I've been
accused in my career of like kind of
creating it too many like boundaries for
creators, like, oh, they can't
experiment, they can't be creative. I'm
like, you can experiment, you can be
creative, just do it one in every four
times or one every five times. If you're
being creative and experimenting and
trying something completely new, you
either have to be a genius, you know,
and great Casey Neistat. I mean, I'm not
going to tell him what to do. He's a
genius. But if you are like mere mortals
like me and like most people, you've got
to think through the lens of like is
there overlap between these topics? So
the 80% strategy overlap rule, it's like
are these topics overlapping? And the
simple question to me is just like, can
80% of people who watch this video watch
this video, watch this video? And that's
really how I think about that.
>> Guys, we've been doing that wrong. Sorry
for the for the listeners out there.
It's definitely not 80%. It's a little
bit lower. Yeah, we try and kind of
blend out on a per guest perspective.
It's not 80%. It's a bit lower, but from
a topic perspective. So, let's go
through. You said 110 one. You start
with the one idea under kind of this
thesis and then how do you kind of
ladder up? And are you saying 100 ideas?
so easily. Yeah. So I would say right
now like at any given time we have about
five to 10 clients. Like we are we take
the approach of like we are like almost
like a boutique law firm that will win
the case. But our case is like growing
your YouTube channel. So we I've just
assembled a team of the smartest people
on YouTube. Like my lead YouTube
strategist right now actually had his
own channel with over a million
subscribers and average like three
million views a video. He quit it to
come work with me. Like we just have
this team of killers that just get
YouTube better than anyone else. And
what we will basically do is we will
take each client and we do the ideation.
So they outsource the ideation to us. So
for each client, we're usually ideating
anywhere between two, three, maybe even
500 ideas for them every month. Now
those are ideas that we ideate. They
don't see that many. They see five,
right? So generally we look at it like
if we if we want to come up with five
ideas, we're probably going to have to
come up with 500. So that's where the
110 one comes from. If you want to come
up with a great idea, you start by
coming up with 100 ideas. And this is
the the sort of concept from Apple,
which is like if we want to launch a
great product or a great feature, like
we've got to like brainstorm a hundred
products and features and then whittle
them down to be left with the one that
is actually going to be the thing that
moves the the lever. So for me with
ideiation going back to that idea we
talked about of internal external
innovation to me that's all about just
getting this big group and source of
ideas that we can put into a funnel. So
when I say come up with 100 ideas I am
literally talking about we have a
spreadsheet month over month for each
clients where four or five different
people are coming up with hundreds of
ideas like every month in the
spreadsheet most of which will never see
the light of day. They're just like what
about this what about that like what if
we try this idea or what if we try that
idea. So 1101 to me is you come up with
100 ideas then you eliminate them down
to like your best 10 using an
elimination criteria. Now that can be a
simple thing like I I actually suggest
every channel has elimination criteria.
You should have elimination criteria for
guests. If it's like
>> we have our own skill on cloud. It's a
guest vetting system where we give like
a blended average based on distribution
communication skills. Does it fit the
ICP? 100%.
>> There you go. There you go. So like
maybe you're if you're a YouTube
channel, maybe your elimination criteria
is like, you know, is this feasible? Can
we easily title thumbnail it? That you
wouldn't believe. Like I when I say we
come up with 500 ideas for a client in a
month, people might be like, that's
overkill, that's over the top. Just by
applying that one criteria of can we put
it into a good title thumbnail, that
could get rid of like twothirds of them
because you can come up with great ideas
and it's like there's not really an easy
way to package that. So many times like
I have like a younger team member, they
come to me, they're like, "Patty, I'm so
bullish on this idea. It's amazing. It's
amazing. I'm like, "Okay, okay." And
they're like, "It's it's so good." I'm
like, "How do we put this in a
thumbnail?" And it's like, "Okay, we're
getting rid of the idea. It doesn't
work." Right. So, guys, we're about to
turn the corner and get into packaging
soon. I completely agree. I want to tell
you this cuz you're going to be proud of
me. So, looking at guests like one of my
buddies who's, you know, nine figure
entrepreneur. I was just with him in New
York and I want to have him on. our main
conversation when you're getting a drink
last week in New York is what's the
packaging concept is like I can sit and
have an interview but if we can't
package it up into something then it's
just it's not going to travel and it's
not worth our time.
>> Yeah,
>> it's about packaging first.
>> 100%. So like your anation creator might
be like is it easy to package? Is it
feasible? You know cuz like quite often
like especially when we're ideating for
clients like Red Bull like my team come
up with ideas I'm like I don't think
it's possible to put a car on the moon
you know like it's great but it's not
feasible. So like feasible could be
different. And it's like I mean, you
know, I'm sure you'd love to have Elon
Musk on the pod. I'm not going to say
you can't, but maybe right now it's less
feasible than other guests, right? So, I
think I always look at like feasibility.
I look at aspirational view target that
can eliminate a lot down as well. So,
setting a view target for your channel,
like if I was you and you know, I know
that I'm averaging 100,000 views an
episode between YouTube and and
downloads, I would look at it and be
like, huh, like what is my aspirational
target? Well, I probably want to get to
like 150 200,000 views an episode. So
now, if you have a guest that comes
along and you're like, I think they're a
good guest, but I think they're probably
going to get like 20 30,000 views. I
don't think there's quite enough
evidence that they can get out there and
get the views that I want. You probably
shouldn't do that episode, as harsh and
strict as that sounds. If your goal is
pure growth, I I'm saying everything
through a lens of like growing the
biggest possible audience, which is not
always the goal, but you know, but
basically, you have this kind of
criteria. I usually suggest it being
like four or five different points. this
idea your ideas have to tick off those
before getting down. If you have 100
ideas, you put them through your funnel,
you put them through the elimination
criteria and you're left with 30, your
elimination criteria is probably
garbage. It's probably just easy to get
through.
>> Needs to be more rigorous, harder to get
through it.
>> Yeah. If you're putting 100 ideas
through and you're left with like one or
two, it's probably too strict. So, you
know, I like to look at the criteria of
like, can we just give ourselves these
five things that a channel a video needs
for our channel? you know, if it doesn't
have this, it we shouldn't make it. An
example for my channel was like my view
target was always a million views. So,
it's very simple. Like I would analyze
these YouTubers and how they grew. Well,
it's kind of interesting if if like the
YouTuber themselves aren't averaging
over a million views a video. It's kind
of unlikely that they're going to get
over a million views a video when I do a
meta analysis on their channel. So, I'm
not going to make videos on creators who
aren't getting over a million views a
video. Like, that's kind of the lens of
through I I look through strategy back
then. So yeah, you got your right
criteria. Hopefully that takes 100
ideas. Maybe leaves you with the 10 ones
that you're looking at of like, okay,
these are the strongest. We've ideated
them. They've gone through the funnel.
They've came down. They've, you know,
we've left with these 10 ideas. From
there, with each of those 10 ideas, I'll
usually do like a one page like idea
slide is what I call them. And it's this
idea of like a rough thumbnail sketch, a
rough title or titles,
>> Jesus.
>> A rough skeleton, a rough kind of like
log line of the video. And these these
are for these 10 ideas. And probably
nine of these 10 videos will never see
the light of day. This is just to get to
a point where now we have like imagine
we have this beautiful wall and we're
putting the 10 ideas and now we have
these 10 different like potential
directions to go or different ideas to
come through. Then we have those 10.
I'll if we have a team, even if I'm a
solo creator, but let's just say we have
a team. I just go, "Okay, everyone,
let's get in the meeting. Which one do
we think if we had to put our career on
one of these videos, which one do we
think is the best? That's the one we'll
make." So to make a video on a channel,
I think most people just think it just
sort of goes like, "Oh, I came up with
this idea. Let's do it." It's like we're
bleeding for ideas. You know, we're
hurting ourselves.
>> For everybody out there listening, we're
not doing enough either, clearly. So to
tie a bow in it, it's kind of you start
with just like knowing your audience,
your ICP. Ladder up as many ideas as
possible, 100, 200, 300, 400. Filter it
down through the elimination criteria.
And then ultimately, you go through this
kind of one-page thing where it has
title, thumbnail, rough sketch. Guys,
we're going to put that one pager down
below in a PDF and then subjectively
everybody in the room is kind of picking
who what are you most excited about? And
you subjectively pick one and and you
let it go.
>> Yeah. And if you're a solo creator, it's
just like out of these 10, if I had to
pick one to put my career on it, like
which would I pick?
>> Gun to the head. I like that.
>> Most creators are just duct taping
together a bunch of different tools to
run their podcast and their newsletter.
Your audience, the analytics, the
attention, it's all split. Everything is
fragmented. This is where Beehive
changed everything for us. It's where
Open Residency runs our newsletter and
they just dropped a new native podcast
tool. [music] Upload your audio and
immediately get distributed to Apple
Podcast and Spotify. If you're hosting
somewhere else, just paste your RSS feed
[music] and your entire back catalog,
the metadata and the episodes all carry
over. One platform, one login,
everything talks to each other. Head to
beehive.com/open
residency for 30% off your first 3
months. [music] Just enter code mark30
at checkout. That's be eh iivi
v.com/open residency and code mark30 at
checkout. Stop renting your audience.
Start [music] owning it.
This episode is brought to you by
Momentous. Most Americans today are
walking around deficient in omega-3,
vitamin D, and magnesium. Three of the
most foundational [music] things in
energy, recovery, and sleep. And even if
you're already taking supplements, the
industry is so loosely regulated that
you really don't know what you're
taking. I know the team behind Momentous
personally, and that's why I trust it.
Every product, every batch is
third-party tested for NSF, certified
for sport. So, what's on the label is
exactly what's in the bottle. It's why
over 200 pro sports teams trust them,
[music] and why my whole stack is
theirs. Omega-3, vitamin D, magnesium,
and creatine every single day. If you're
putting real effort into your health,
you want to know that it's actually
working. Go to livemus.com. Use code
openresidency for up to 35% off your
first order.
Let's double click on packaging because
I think everybody that has listened thus
far is thinking that they're not they're
not doing enough and I think you would
agree that packaging is everything. We
talked about it being a click and watch
platform YouTube. If they don't click,
they don't watch. You've said a 20%
better title can earn a 100 time more
views, not 20 times more views. Why is
that true? And why do people really not
act on it? So there's this idea, it's
kind of like the nonlinear returns idea
I have for content, which is basically
algorithms are multipliers, right? The
YouTube algorithm has like this
multiplication effect where essentially
if something is a little bit better, it
might be enough better to then reach,
you know, so much of a wider audience
because of how broad and exponential
YouTube algorithm is. And it's kind of
like this in a lot of disciplines,
right? like the the best the player that
makes it in the NBA, they're usually not
like five times better than the player
that doesn't, right? But they're like
maybe 10% better in all the right ways.
They're a little bit faster, they're a
little bit stronger, they're a little
bit more consistent. The player that
doesn't make it or they make it semi-pro
playing in Thailand, you know,
>> close.
>> Yeah, it's close. Maybe they're making
>> 50k a year. The player that makes the
NBA, maybe they're making 10 million a
year. And it's like, well, he's only 10
or 20% better than the other guy, but
he's 10 or 20 10 or 20% better in a sort
of exponential game with nonlinear
returns. And I think the beautiful thing
about YouTube is is it isn't predictable
linear. It's not like, oh, if we make it
10% better, it gets 10% more views. It's
like, no, it it can actually occur where
you make something a little bit better
and it gets 100 times more views. We
have this real example where we had
someone in our training program and he
was this like web designer channel. His
name was Gabe and I'm sure we can show
an example of it in the pod. And he had
a video that was doing about a thousand
views a day and it had like a decent
thumbnail, like a pretty good thumbnail.
My team sat down with him, brainstormed
a new idea, he came with a new
thumbnail, changed the thumbnail. So,
this is this isn't even on a new video.
This is on a video that already existed,
that was already out there and was
getting a,000 views a day. Within a day
of changing the thumbnail, that video
went from getting a,000 views a day to
40,000 views a day. And it's like 40
times more views basically with one
change. And like if you look at the
thumbnails side by side, I think if you
just ask people on the street, they
would say, "Yeah, the new one's like a
bit better." Like it's like, you know,
it's reasonably better. It's like maybe
20 30% better, but it led to, you know,
40 times more views. And I think it's
just the fact that the YouTube algorithm
is this multiplier. Like Jimmy, Mr.
Beast, is the biggest creator in the
world. He puts more effort and time in
than anyone else. But I wouldn't say
you'd look at his video and say it's
like a hundred times better than this
creator or that creator. It's like no,
he's just understanding that he's
playing an exponential game, a nonlinear
game.
>> What percent of time on packaging?
>> So I like to say packaging is 50% of the
game. I don't think it should be 50% of
the time because that's kind of insane.
But I would say let's just say let's
just say you have 100 hours to make a
YouTube video, right? Where should you
put that time? If I was like ale, if I
was a time allocator and I have 100
hours, where would I put it? I think I
would put 10 to 20 hours of that time
towards packaging. And the the
interesting thing about that is like
people will say, well, how like how like
how do you spend 20 hours making one
image? It's like, okay, well, we don't
make one image, we're making 50, right?
Or we don't just make the image, we
research every other, you know, title or
thumbnail in our niche and see what we
can take from them. We're spending hours
researching. We're hiring a designer to
come in and like come up with other
ideas. We're like studying movie posters
from the 80s, you know, it's like it's
not just as simple as like making images
for a thumbnail or writing titles for a
title. But yeah, I think anywhere
between 10 or 20% of the total time we
spend on clients is on on the packaging.
We'll often write like I I say this,
this actually frustrates me. I I'll say
like we write 50 titles for a video
sometimes. People like you're insane.
You're clinically insane. What's wrong
with you? I'm like it doesn't take that
long to write 50 titles. Like
>> it doesn't we're good with that for
titles and thumbnails. We go we go
pretty hard on that.
>> Good. I feel like the big thing and
we're talking about packaging. Please
add if if I'm missing any title,
thumbnail, and idea. And I feel like
idea is the one that we don't spend
enough time on. Is there anything else
kind of big under title, thumbnail, idea
under prepackaging?
>> Yeah, like that's spot on. The one thing
I would add that's actually kind of
interesting is it's not only your idea,
title, thumbnail. It's how people
enjoyed your last video. You know,
that's that's quite important. Like
think about it from your behavior. If
you really enjoy the person's last
video, then you see them again, you
click it cuz you're like, "Oh, I really
like their last video." And this
actually creates sometimes quite
interesting things for me because like I
always talk about these like, you know,
how much time we're putting into
thumbnails, how like, you know, oh,
we're spending like 10 grand on this
thumbnail. We're like doing all this
crazy stuff and then someone's like,
"Look at the outdoor boys. He's just
posting a screenshot or look at this
channel. They're not even trying." And
they'll get so many views. And it's like
sometimes like the content is so good
and the creator is so good that the
brand of the thumbnail even if it's a
bad thumbnail just becomes recognizable
and the person's just like I want to
click that. So that's like an
interesting thing. Sometimes you might
contend with this at a certain point. we
might realize that like oh wow like
people have become used to clicking our
style of thumbnail and now we're sort of
assessing it and saying there's probably
a more optimal style of thumbnail for
the podcast but if we do it then people
won't know it's us and then that becomes
like this this difficult game where you
start to AB test and and play around
with different options.
>> We're we're actually there right now and
it's about just kind of incrementally
changing things. So, we'll keep kind of
the POV of the guest on the same color
theme, but now like on the left, as
opposed to it being very kind of clean
and brand from a typography perspective,
we're now adding like images like we'll
pop up right now the Peter Rahal
thumbnail with like David Protein. They
went through this whole entire lawsuit
that got resolved and that thumbnail
among other reasons. I mean, it's going
nuclear right now. And that was like we
tested 80% of it was the same. The one
thing we changed was like, hey, let's
put images on the left side. So yeah, I
think you have to be incremental because
you don't want to lose all that kind of
brand equity that you've got from the
past of people recognizing what the
aesthetic looks like.
>> Yeah.
>> Like changing the color that would be
bold cuz we're like people, you know,
know our color. Let's show this in
practice. So I want to pop up here a
thumbnail that you did with Red Bull
that went absolutely nuclear and I want
to just kind of walk through why it did
so well. Title, thumbnail, ideation,
where did it start? Tell us everything.
>> 100%. What one of my favorite things
about this screenshot is this is a month
after the video was posted, right? And
it's on 18 million views.
>> I think it's on like 30 now. It's on
like 30 or 40 now. It's like
>> disrespectful. We're going to re put up
a new one with 30 million views.
>> But I think there's a few things, right?
Like first of all, the idea is great.
World's fastest camera drone versus F1
car. Like look, world's fastest camera
drone. Like fastest is a superlative
camera drone versus F1 car. If you
associate F1 car with the fastest thing
on earth, so that's interesting. What's
going to win that battle? Max Versappen
is the greatest driver in the world in
my opinion, you know, that's obviously
lending a huge amount of credibility to
the title. So all those things are
obvious, right? Like and I almost say
those because people contend. They're
like that would have always gone viral
on the matter of the thumbnail. And like
I, you know, my our thumbnail designer,
I shouldn't say my our thumbnail
designer Britney, who's in my opinion
the best thumbnail designer in the
world, she made this thumbnail. And I'm
like, that has a huge impact on this
video because if it's actually
interesting, I had an argument about
this video and about how we're going to
package it. And someone else had like a
different title thumbnail idea and it
was still a good idea, but I just
remember saying, I think with your title
from my idea, this video is going to get
a million views. I think with the one we
want to go forward with, I think this
video can get 10 million views plus. And
I felt so confident. And that's the
thing. It's like people will sometimes
contend and be like, "Oh, it's a fast
camera drone versus an F1 cover versus
Max for stop and of course it's going to
go viral." It's like, do you know how
many videos out there have like all the
ingredients to be great, but they're not
packaged well and they just get no
views? Like super common. So, what I
love about it, great title, pause and
action, right? Click to unpause. You
have to click that video. It feels like
you're actually seeing the start of a a
video right there. You feel like you're
you're seeing them revving up right
beside the start line. You're clicking
to just make that scene happen. got
these like beautiful leading lines into
the horizon that are just directing your
focus towards the the the race itself.
And look how simple it is. It's just
clean, right? It's not over complicated.
Max Rosappen is
probably top three most famous drivers
in the world. Like very recognizable
face. Didn't put him in the thumbnail,
right? Like because the actual thumb
stuff didn't need them.
>> Also under the notion that you probably
don't want to double up on kind of
themes or POVs. if you want to kind of
use all the real estate there to kind of
hit different senses. I would say
>> 100%.
>> I love the idea of like yeah like you're
at the starting line or you're just
waiting for it to start and it like it
like baits you into like I have to click
to start the race. Click click to
unpause and unpause and unpause and
unpause and pause like that that concept
click to unp
say that and this is another great
example right like we have okay we have
a video here with an F1 car and a drone
and max for stappen that's probably cost
you know an insane amount of money all
this access incredible right and it was
uploaded to a channel with tens of
millions subscribers so a lot of people
are going to look at that and be like oh
click to unpause that sounds great like
how am I going to do that with my small
podcast or how am I going to do that
with my health and wellness company or
or whatever and what's interesting is
like you can do click to unpause for a
podcast. So, if I look at your
thumbnails, they're kind of click to
unpause and pause, right? It's someone
speaking and it's generally like a quote
or it's something beside them, right? If
you look at like some of the biggest
podcasts as well, they they're like
someone mid speech, right? If if it was
like poised, if I was for our thumbnail
for this video, right? If I just sort of
stood there and I was like, "Hey,"
smiling at the camera,
that's not click to unpause. Well,
you're clicking to unpause some like
idiot just with his thumb up. But if I'm
like talking like this and there's like
some text here, it's like, "Oh, I'm
clicking to unpause on pause him saying
what it's saying in the thumbnail." So,
you can use it in so many different
niches. Like, it's not just action.
Yeah. And to unpack this for people out
there listening like talking about kind
of taking external videos and then
making it yours. Like, I feel like I've
seen, you know, other YouTubers like
they're be a random YouTuber and they're
racing like Usain Bolt. Like, you could
say like they loosely took that idea off
of this. Yeah. Yeah.
>> So, like there's just a million
different concepts within this concept
that you can just kind of drag into your
own
>> and we loosely concept from a channel
called CarWow in the UK which does drag
races between cars, right? It's like we
were thinking of so many different
concepts and we were like look Carwow
does these lineup films where they have
the car and then you have like this you
know thing like the other car behind
let's sort of adapt that and try our
version of that. So everything is kind
of an adaptation of other things that
work.
>> Makes sense. So packaging idea title
thumbnail. Let's kind of walk through
the full packaging workflow from the
moment when you have the idea to
actually hitting publish just from like
from a macro perspective.
You have the ideas, then what? How do
you go title, thumbnail? Like what's
that kind of order of how you do things?
>> So workflow to me is this. You have your
idea. Next up,
>> you have your 500 ideas that turn into
one turn into one idea.
>> You have your 500 You have your your
idea gladiator that's that survive 500
ideas in a fight to the death and it's
been left there. All right, at that
point you have an idea. To me, the next
step is titles first. So, some people
like come up with a thumbnail first. In
my opinion, it's always better to come
up with the title first because then
that's sort of like saves you the time
of having to work on the thumbnail. And
also, like when you have your title, you
can start to inform what the thumbnail
should be because the thumbnail should
complement the title, right? So, I'll
come up with titles first. I like to
encourage people to do a minimum of 10
titles. So simple. It's like, you know,
world's fastest camera drone versus F1
car. like camera drone versus F1 car
featuring Max for Mappen. Max Fappen
races world's fastest camera drone with
his F1 car, you know, like there's so
many different titles. Like I I just
said five in like 5 seconds. It's like
it doesn't take that long to come up
with a lot of titles. I like to just sit
there and say what are the different
ways I can tile them. We can we can get
into like the title principles I use in
a second as well. But simple 10 titles,
you got your titles. Next up, thumbnail
brief. So just like how you have like a
photography brief or like a shoot brief
for like a you know production or or
whatever it might be we'll create a
document that we will hand to our
clients which basically says here are
the five concepts to shoot in this
video. What's really interesting is the
vast majority of people and I would say
even creators that have millions of
subscribers big budgets they still to
this day and it drives me insane. I
don't get it. They'll still just shoot
the video and then afterwards be like
okay what's the thumbnail? And I'm like,
[sighs]
so we do these thumbns first where we'll
be like, these are the five images we
need you to capture on the day. So, oh,
you're making a video with the
Philadelphia Eagles with with Jaylen
Hertz or you're you're making this video
with an F1 car or whatever. We want it
from these angles. We want it to be
posed like this. We'll like draw up
these concepts because you're either
sketched. We'll like handdraw them.
Sometimes they're sketched. We'll use
image generation with AI to like give
sort of rough ideas of what we're
looking for. Even I have like committed
absolute like artistry crimes making
thumbnails before just with like
terrible stick figures, but just
something to be like this is what we're
we're roughly looking for. So that's the
thumbnail brief. That's step number two
in the workflow. You have the thumbnail
brief, then you go shoot the thumbnail.
So that's just taking the photos. Now
the interesting thing at this stage,
again, this is a thing that sort of
frustrates me is just like I I'll be
like we'll take like I don't know like
three or 4 hundred photos for a
thumbnail and then everyone's like what?
Like why do you do that? I'm like like
if I just take my phone out like right
like
okay I just took 11 photos of you like
in slightly different poses slightly
different micro expressions. So when I'm
asking like a creative to shoot a
thumbnail. I'm like let's get it from
different angles. Let's get them like
facing a little bit different way. Let's
try different lighting. So I'm just like
for each of these concepts let's say in
our thumb brief we have five concepts.
like I'll want like 10, 20, 30 different
shots in different angles or different
positions for each of those thumbnails.
And then after that, we'll take the
source and then you go into the design
phase. And you know, you've got your
your thumb shoot done. You go into
thumbnail design and that is going back
to the original brief looking at the
source and picking at least three
separate different thumbnails that you
are going to create from that source and
designing and fully designing three
different thumbnails at least. So, like
I said earlier, we have worked on videos
recently where we have made 50, 45, 50
thumbnails. That does happen. But also,
it's expensive, takes a lot of time, not
always feasible. So, what I like to say
is everyone should have time to make
three thumbnails. Even if you're a
beginner creator that only has like 10,
20 hours a week to do this. You know,
even if you're like a business owner
who's just hired like a strategist to do
this, you can probably still afford to
put time into having three thumbnails
for your videos. Like for your podcast,
I'm sure you come up with a lot more
than three. Yeah, I mean one of 10 has a
thumbnail generator. It's pretty good.
And like that is one thing that
obviously you can come up with the
ideas, but outsourcing to really really
good thumbnail people, it's not crazy
expensive for people out there listening
like a couple hundred bucks. And I think
to double click on what you're saying,
this all leads back to following the
data. So like when you're talking about
thumbnails, like we've seen like should
they wear a hat, should they not wear a
hat, should there be a logo, should
there not be a logo, are they smiling,
are they serious? And then just like
really, you know, the more data,
internal data that you have, you start
kind of seeing patterns and just kind of
iterating off that. So yeah, I can only
imagine when we have like a hundred
interviews in, we're just going to have
so much data on what works and what
doesn't.
>> Yeah. And then AB testing every single
one and then like going back and AB
testing them and being like, I wonder if
I move the text down a little bit or
whatever. It's like I think people would
assume that the the best people on
YouTube are the most creative. And
sometimes that's true, but I think quite
often they're actually more like
architects, engineers, than pure like
creatives like you might see in
Hollywood. Like if you ask me like
someone like a Mr. Beast, like he is an
engineer. He's engineering virality.
He's studying every angle, every way he
can open a video, every way he can
thumbnail a video to find the best
video. And even for me myself, like I
think I'm a creative person. Like my
parents are both writers. I used to want
to be a like a a writer. That was like
my biggest best skill in school actually
was English. But I sort of think I view
it through the lens of like an analyst
and like a a data analyst of like what
are the trends? What's the pattern
recognition? One of my friends owned a
very big performance marketing company.
He spends a lot of time with me and he's
just like dude I think you the skills
you're using for this are kind of the
same skills as performance marketing.
It's like the different ad copy like
tweaking things, testing it. Okay, if I
if I like have the ad running at this
time of day, if I use this text, if I
use this color, does it convert better?
It's like that's the same thing with
packaging. It's like the same game.
>> I completely agree. I feel like the
title should be like creative analyst
100%.
>> Yeah.
>> And I feel like the people that are
getting the asymmetric outcomes in this
world usually are creative first and
they're not leaning on the analytics and
these kind of principles and frameworks
that Patty is giving you all in this
episode. That is how you win is you're
taking all these frameworks and making
it objective, not like so subjective. To
tie a bow on that, what is the minimum
amount of titles and thumbnails people
should have when they put out a video? I
think minimum 10 titles, three
thumbnails. Like I actually I don't have
it in my contracts anymore, but for a
certain point I had it as a contract
line item that like it's a
non-negotiable. You're going to make
three thumbnails a video. If you don't,
I'm just not going to sign you as a
client.
>> Like
>> under the notion that you want to be set
up for success. Like if they don't do
that, then you can't even do your job.
>> Yeah. I'm like I don't like cuz cuz I
like I don't care about the the
business. Like I do care about the
business of course, but like I care my
my whole career is built on case studies
and growing channels. So, I I go fully
in on the channels we work with and I'm
like, I want to grow this channel to be
the biggest channel in the world. So, if
you're not willing to make three
thumbnails per video, like, you're not
gonna be our client. Doesn't matter if
you want to pay us 100,000 a month,
we're not gonna take it.
>> Yeah. Out of 10 titles, let's call it
six thumbnails. You probably should have
more than three. Six thumbnails. You
press go and you publish. What does that
look like? It's 8:00 a.m. PST. What does
it look like in Patty's World once you
press publish?
>> Depends on the channel. So, with the big
channels we work in, like we had a I'm
not going to name the channel, but we
had a video recently where in the first
day it did 4 million views and it was a
failure. People were like, "What's
happening? It's not working. Must be
nice." So, it depends on the channel,
right? But basically, the way I like to
think about it, you post the video. I
always like to just pick the You come up
with 10 titles. I like to pick the one
title I feel the strongest about. If we
have a team, we'll discuss it together.
Which one title would we put our career
behind as having the best chance of
working? Pick that title. Leave that
alone for now. Put that title in. Put
your best three thumbnails in into your
AB test. A little thing I would always
like to say as well is like I'm looking
for like differentiated thumbnails. I'm
not just looking. What I see sometimes
is like I'm like make three thumbnails
and someone's like, "Okay." Then they
make three thumbnails and the only thing
that changes the shirt color. It's like,
you know, you just took the same shot
and just put me in a white, a yellow,
and a blue t-shirt. Like that's not
change. That's not three different
thumbnails. So three differentiated
thumbnails. To me, I I love YouTube
testing natively. Some people don't
enjoy it as much or, you know, have
mixed experience with it. I use it with
every client. That's all I can say. You
know, we we work across a billion views
a month and we use it with every client.
So, I love native AB testing on YouTube.
I'll upload those three thumbnails. I'll
press publish and basically the minute
before I press publish, I'm just making
sure I'm really aligned on the expected
view performance of the video. So, what
I'll actually do, it's really
interesting with our clients. We'll have
like the video then we'll have the team
members and everyone is predicting the
views of the video in the first let's
say well usually the first hour the
first day and the first week and the
reason I love to do that before I press
upload is because if we have a video
that we think should be the best video
we've ever made. We think it should be
like a one out of 10. How am I even
getting to that point? Well, it's a bit
of like, you know, feeling data. Has it
worked in the past? Like if you have
Elon on your podcast, you're going to be
like this should be a one out of 10.
Like surely this should be the best
video we've ever made, right? So if you
post that video and it comes out the
gates and it's a 2 out of 10 and for
people listening that means it's the
second best video out of the last 10
videos you posted in the YouTube ranking
system, you should change the thumbnail.
You should do it should be panic
stations, right? It's like you know when
Mr. Beast made Squid Game, like if he if
he posted that video and it was a three
out of 10, technically a three out of 10
is above average, but it's not for the
expectation of that video. And on the
flip side, sometimes a creator has a
video where they're like, "Yeah, I know
this isn't going to work. like, I know
it's not going to really work that well.
It's a smaller topic. I still want to
post it, though. I'm like, okay, great.
Let's post it. They'll post it. It's an
8 out of 10. They're like, "Shit, what?
What the [__] Why isn't it working? We
need to change something." I'm like,
it's it's not just about where it ranks
against your last videos. It's where it
ranks against your expectation. So,
before I press publish, I make sure that
I am aligned and the team is aligned
with like where do we expect this video
to fall? Like, roughly, we get it wrong
all the time. It's not it's not a
perfect science, but it's like I think
this is should be I remember posting
this video and being like it probably
should be a one out of 10. It could be a
two out of 10 because we posted another
video before that also did really well,
but it should be a 1 out of 10. If it
came out of the gates as a 4 out of 10,
we should probably stop that AB test and
just try a new one altogether. Like we
should probably just make a dramatic
change because if it's not working, you
know, as quickly as as that, we could
make that decision. So, a lot of it is
about the expected outcome. But usually
what I'll do is I'll set the expectation
out outcome. I'll run the the thumbnail
test. I'll let the thumbnail test pick a
winner. I'll make sure that winner is
selected as the main thumbnail. And if
I'm not happy with performance, I might
try some different titles as well. But
generally, that's my approach to it.
>> Wow. So, you don't go back to the title
and test the test the title again once
you've logged in the thumbnail.
>> If it's underperforming expectation,
that's the whole thing, right? because
it's like it is a thing where I know we
just talked about like how you can be a
little bit of like a an engineer and try
all these different things, but like if
a video is performing well and above
where we expect it to perform. It's kind
of this thing of like, you know, if you
have good data, good data is always
better than no data, right? So, if you
have good data, which is basically this
tile is working, the video is doing
better. This tile we have no data on
because we haven't post published it
yet.
>> Don't want to shake the boat.
>> Good data better than no data. On the
flip side of that though, what's
interesting is like sometimes like
people will post a video and it will be
doing bad. So now you have bad data and
then you have no data on the one you
haven't tried yet and they'll be like,
"Oh, I just want to give it a bit more
time." Like I and I'm just like, "Okay,
well now we have bad data versus no
data." No data is better than bad data
cuz like the no data might be good. We
don't know. It could also be bad, but we
don't know. So in that situation, I will
make the change. So I do generally
suggest to move away from this sort of I
think a few years ago people on YouTube
in general were just like changing the
title like 10 times in the first day
changing the thumbnail so many times.
It's like at that point like I don't
even know what's causing the impact then
like if I'm changing things that much
like how do I know it was the title? How
do I know it's not just like the the
fact that like you know something else
was happening in the background? Like
there's so many external factors on
YouTube like maybe I don't know right
when you posted maybe another person
posted a podcast that people are
watching and now after they've watched
that podcast they're getting you
suggested next and that's all coming in
but you've changed the title just before
that and now you're like oh [__] the
title works but it's like is it or is it
you know this other factor so I I
generally steer away from changing too
much like unless if the video is
dramatically underperforming expectation
I'll go to war a little bit and I'll
I'll make some big changes. I think the
the second layer to that is absolutely
amazing advice to anybody out there on
creator operator YouTube side. Uh the
expectations is huge. I think it goes
back to like you shouldn't probably do a
concept or have a guess that you don't
think could be at least a five out of
10. Obviously there could be like
external reasons why you do something,
but like if you're going in thinking
it's going to be eight or nine or 10 out
of 10 on one of 10, probably shouldn't
have that guest on to begin with.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Or you should have a very
good reason, right? It's like, think
about this any like I just I just did a
a tweet on my Twitter account and like I
view my Twitter just the same as I view
YouTube. I think these skills just
translate across the board. Like I I
view Twitter is like, okay, I average
about 200,000 views per tweet on Twitter
or X, I should say. Do I think this
tweet's going to do better? Do I think
it's going to do worse? I did a tweet
last week which is promoting like my
program. I know that's going to do
worse, but I'm still going to post it
because it's it's got a huge potential
upside for me. But I'm not going to post
a lot of them, right? I'm going to post
that once every now and again and the
other ones are going to make sure. So
there there are sometimes situations
where it does make sense to post videos
that you don't think are going to get as
many views. People have sometimes called
me like the the view maximalist. Like I
just think about view maximizing
everything. View max, right? It's like
views, views, views. They're like Patty
just doesn't understand that there's
like value to like smaller niche
audiences. I'm like there is. There
totally is. But sometimes the people
that say that are the people that can't
get the views. Just saying. Like it
depends. Like if if you are in a if you
are in a niche where like it makes sense
to be more niche and smaller, like I get
it. Like there is a value to like, you
know, if if you're like a high netw
worth accountant, I don't care if you're
getting a million views in your videos.
You just care about the 1,000 viewers
who have a high ultra net worth, ultra
high net worth. Like you care about the
people who are buying yachts and boats
or whatever. Like sure, then make videos
that are reaching as many of those
people as you can. Like, but for a lot
of people, I think there is a value to
just trying to trying to see how big the
niche and TAM can be. I think
regardless, playing the one of 10 game
is important because it's it's really
you versus you, not you versus the
external. It's just knowing that you're
incrementally doing better than you did
from the past. Because if you're not
going up and to the right, I think
you're doing something wrong.
>> Yep.
>> So on the title side, principles,
framers, what are the specific things
that you're looking at in a title? Like
what's that filter under the notion that
you're not changing the title most of
the time? Looks like you're obviously
testing the thumbnail. So what do you
look for in a title to make sure that it
can go live?
>> Yeah. So fewest words possible while
still making it interesting. So
a while ago I used to say keep it to
under 50 characters cuz that's what I
would typically do. I'm a little bit
more lenient on that now. Like a lot of
YouTube right now is watched on TV where
you might have a bit more display room
for titles. I think generally if your
title is like 60 characters plus is a
bit long. Sometimes I'll I'll like push
people to keep it under 60 but there are
still times I'll do that over. But
that's why I come to that principle of
like as few words as possible to make it
interesting. Use universal language.
This is actually a really interesting
thing which is like depending on how
global your audience is or how broad
your audience is, everyone has a curse
of knowledge bias. So everyone sort of
assumes people know the things that they
know. Right? So if I said the word D1
athlete to you, you'd be like I don't
know what that is. Right? Three years
ago I did not know what that was. So if
someone said D1 athlete, I'd be like
what's that? I don't know what that is.
I'm from Ireland. Like oh college
athlete. Okay. I get that. So, if you're
making a video and you have like, you
know, more than half of your viewers
outside the USA and you title a video
that says, I don't know, D1 athlete
tries viral like workout techniques for
the first time. I'm here in Ireland. If
I'm here in England or Europe or
Australia, I might be like, "What's a D1
athlete? That's weird. I don't know what
that is." Pro athlete, I can understand.
Right. Same with like, you know, I
didn't know what Goodwill was. You know,
like a Goodwill store. Yeah. Like, so
there was a guy that made this video and
he's like, I made this video and it was
like, I went to Goodwill and like built
this thing from Goodwill or something.
And I was like, what the [__] is a good
what what's a Goodwill? And he's like,
oh, it's a store. It's like this, you
know, very famous store here in America.
And I looked into the analytics for him
and it was so interesting. The video had
just had done just as well as Norman in
the USA, but he had just missed all of
his like Asian viewers, his European
viewers, and all these things because
everyone's like, "What is Goodwill? I
don't know what that is." Like it wasn't
it's not a thing, you know? So
>> under that lens, it's just how do you
not shrink your TAM? You want the
biggest possible TAM.
>> Yes. Yes. And of of course there's like
there's limits to it where it's like,
you know, sometimes for example like if
you are let's just say a business
channel, right? You know, if you're
putting like ebida and like these terms
in your title, you might be shrinking
your time a little bit. If you want to
reach those
>> Oh boy, I hear you guys out there. Need
more definitions up here.
>> If if you want to if you want to reach
those fears, it can work, right? But
like I don't think let's just say Dire
SEO like one of the biggest business
podcasts in the world, right? If not the
biggest. Don't really think he'd put
Ebida in a title. I don't think so. Like
he put profit, he put money, right? But
like so it's about like your audience
and who you're trying to reach. if you
if you are trying to reach a more like
qualified audience, it's fine to use
like jargon and terminology like that.
But like yeah, I I would say if I went
down the street here in in LA and and
interviewed 100 people and asked them
what EBIT that was and define it, they'd
be like maybe five people would know it
out of 100, 5%. You know, so if you're
if you're going for a broad audience,
it's going to limit you. So for
>> everybody out there listening, TAM is
total addressable market. Just continue.
Sorry.
>> There you go. Yeah.
>> So that's a big one. Use universal
language. Your to should always
complement the thumbnail. So, you need
to think about your title and thumbnail
together. That's why I say come up a
title first and then look at the
thumbnail and make sure they're
complement each other. Generally, I
don't like to repeat the information in
the title that's in the thumbnail. So,
let's just say that you titled this
episode how anyone can go viral in 2026.
I probably would suggest against putting
that as also the thumbnail text because
then it's just like repeating itself. is
not complimenting itself like you know
if I if I saw the title being how anyone
can go viral in 2026 and then the
thumbnail text said like this is the key
or something it's not great but this is
the key those are complnting each other
you read that then you're like this is
the key what's the key I need to click
so complement the thumbnail that's a
really important one
readable at a glance that this is goes
back to that original point of like
people are reading your they're not even
reading your title let's be honest
they're just like scanning it they're
like is that something is that something
I want to watch scroll scroll scroll
So, kind of going back to our point of
like use as few words as possible. Use
words that are very readable, like
contemporary. Okay, that's a very long
word. It doesn't look great in a title.
Modern is probably a better word, right?
Generally, I avoid titles that have like
heavy like segmentation or truncation,
like divided up into three titles. I've
seen these people make titles where it's
like three different titles all like
meshed in together. I like my titles to
be clean, simple, easy to read,
generally shorter words. Generally, I
like to use something that I call it's
called title case formatting where I'll
capitalize the first letter of each word
unless it's like a connecting word like
and or is or on just because it's more
readable. If you use all caps, the
interesting about all caps, I never even
realized this before, but all caps makes
every letter the same height and it
makes it less readable. Like when you
look at an all caps thing, if I just
showed you like a piece of paper and
it's all all caps and I give you like a
second to read it, you're going to be
able to remember less than if it was in
title case. So, I'm always looking for
things that can just make it so my
viewer can just really quickly process
what's on screen. If you look at any
video with over 100 million views, I
guarantee you you look at the title and
you're like, "Oh, I can understand that
right away." It's super readable, simple
words, easy to understand. I do the same
thing with my notes for the podcast,
too. It's got to be quick and readable
at glance. And it's actually why I bold
certain words so I can do a quick glance
down as opposed to, you know, having to
spend 10 seconds reading something.
>> 100%.
>> Same thing, please. And then the final
one and this is like the most important
of all which is like
I think sometimes people
are trying to make YouTube this sort of
check the box thing and look frameworks
are really important like what we're
doing here and like like I said it is
kind of a it's an analyst's game so
that's great but at the same time I'll
tell you about I don't want to throw
anyone under the bus here but my my my
my
biggest frustration are these ideas
called like SEO optimizer tools. that
just like people put their title in an
SEO optimizer and it comes out with a
title and they're like, "Okay, that's
what I'm going to use." It's like,
"Well, first of all, how much traffic on
YouTube actually comes from search." For
most channels, it's like 10%. If even,
right? It's it's it's quite often less.
It's one of my favorite things to tell
people. It's like, how many views come
from subscriber boxes? Less than 5%. How
many views come from the channel page?
About 3%. How many views come from
search? For most channels, about 5 to
10%. There are some channels that get
50% plus from search, but that's rare.
For most channels, it's about 5 to 10%.
So why would you optimize your title for
an SEO score that you know is going to
make a rank rank rank in search? And the
cost of that is making a title that's
absolute garbage, right? iPhone. If you
had a video where you're reviewing the
new iPhone 16, right? Which is a better
title? Like new 2026 iPhone 16 review uh
unboxing tutorial or don't waste your
money reviewing the new iPhone 16.
Right? Both of those still have like the
iPhone 16 keywords. So, they still can
both rank in search. The first one
technically has a better SEO score
because it's jammed full of keywords,
but no human I know would click that
video versus the don't waste your money
one cuz the don't waste your money one
you're like that doesn't actually tell
me the right thing. It's like is the
phone a waste of money or like is it
about picking the right version of the
new iPhone or whatever? So, you're
playing on human interest. And an
example I like to give give on this is
like you know a while ago people did say
including me keep a keep a title to
under 50 characters right but again
that's sort of doing the same thing
where you're trying to appease a sort of
like system or like a an SEO score or
like a title like optimizer score or
something. What is the most interesting
title for a human to click on? That's
always a thing. So we can actually do
like a kind of a live demo. Let's just
say you have a video which is like
called the best value Porsche GT3 on the
market, right? That's your video. So,
what's that title? Okay, the best value
Porsche GT3 on the market. It's not
great. It's not that interesting. Would
you click that? Probably not. Even if
you're a car guy, you're like,
"Whatever." Okay, let's make it a little
bit better. What if you said, "I found
the best value Porsche GT3 on the
market." Okay, now the I found creates a
bit of a story. So, okay, there's a bit
more in there, but still best value GT3
on the market. That's quite generic,
right? How about I found the cheapest
911 GT3 on the market. Now you're adding
a superlative. Now it becomes more
interesting. You're like I found gives
you a story. Cheapest superlative
desirable thing 911 GT3. Okay. Cheapest
GT3. But what if we made it longer while
actually making it better? I found the
cheapest 911 GT3 on the market, but
nobody will buy it. Right. Dot dot dot.
But nobody will buy it. Right. Adam.
>> Okay. What does that do? It makes the
title longer. So technically it gets a
worse score if you're just looking at
the, you know, purely at the the length
of the title. But what does it actually
do? It creates a human interest, which
is like, wait, this thing is the
cheapest. Superlative, unique, right?
Okay, great. This thing is the cheapest
thing. I want to see this thing, but
nobody wants it. You can apply the
inverse, right? I found the worst
apartment in New York City and it's
expensive, but everyone wants to move
in. You'd be like, well, why does
everyone want to move into the worst
apartment, right? like or I found the
cheapest apartment but nobody wants to
move in. It's like creating this
contradiction that's playing on a human
interest. It's it's playing on a human
emotion to be like why is that
interesting? Like why why why would
nobody want the cheapest 911 on the
market? What's wrong with it? Does it
have like some serious damage? Has it
been flooded? Like suddenly all these
these ideas come to your mind. Click go
back to that original title and compare
it. Like look at those two titles side
by side. It's like it can be a different
game.
>> Yeah. I feel like the principles in
frameworks bring you like zero to 80. to
go from 80 to 100, you need curiosity,
taste, analytics, have really, really
good ideas because what you just did was
was nuclear. So, it's it's completely
different. Makes a lot of sense. And
we're going to pop up kind of going
through that whole entire sequence on it
goes good, better, best for sure. So,
you have these title principles, you
upload it. What are you looking on one
of 10 to see how it's performing? What
are those like key metrics that you're
looking at?
>> So, I always say this thing, most
important metric on YouTube is views.
So, people are always like, you know,
whenever I'm at an event, I'm actually
going to VidCon this week, and you know,
I already guarantee you someone's going
to corner me in the hallway and be like,
"Patty, what's the most important metric
to look at in YouTube studio?" And
they're like, "No, no, no, don't don't
don't tell me. I'm going to guess. I'm
going to guess. Is it a secure, right?
Or is it a views per viewer?" I'm like,
"It's views." Like, it's kind of like
asking the question of like, "What's the
most important metric in a business?"
It's kind of revenue and profit, right?
Like ultimately everything, lots of
other things like your cost of
acquisition, your lifetime ROI, all
these things are really important,
right? But like ultimately like that's
probably the most important metric to be
paying attention to. So views as a
metric. I can you can blindfold me for
metrics. Basically you can say Patty all
you have to do to grow a channel is look
at the views. Don't look at CTR. Don't
look at AVD. Don't look at anything
else. I could grow that channel. I don't
need those other things. Like they're
they're really not that important. And
an example I like to give with uh so
something like CTR, right? There's a big
difference between saying AVD and CTOR
don't matter versus saying AVD and CTR
as a metric are very hard to focus on.
So for people watching, CTR means
click-through rate, the amount of people
clicking a video. And AVD means average
view duration, how long that person is
viewing for. And we've all been trained
that those are the most important things
on YouTube, clicks and watches. True.
But the interesting thing is the actual
metric you're displayed in your YouTube
studio, it's kind of misleading because
let's use this example. Let's just say
you have a lemonade stand. Let's say you
put that lemonade stand in front of your
house at home where you grew up. I grew
up in the countryside in Ireland. Lovely
little like, you know, countryside
community, you know, lower middle class.
People walking by. Everyone likes to
support each other. So, I got my
lemonade stand outside my house. My
conversion rate is probably going to be
really good because they're my
neighbors. I know them. My family walk
by. Maybe I'll have like a 20%
conversion rate. If I put that same
lemonade down in New York in Times
Square, New York, my conversion rate is
probably going to drop through the
floor, but I'm getting more sales
because there's more customers, right?
So, CTO, like sometimes people are like,
"Oh, clickthrough rate is so important.
CTOR is so important." Like, oh, let me
like I need to aim for 10% or I heard
that Mr. Beast gets 15% CTR and oh,
let's aim for that. It's like some of
the biggest channels I've ever worked on
have some of the lowest CTRs because
they're operating in the biggest
markets. So, CTR and same with AVD, you
know, average duration. Well, okay. You
want to get really high average view
duration, make a 3-hour video. Like,
does that mean it's better than a
30-minute video? Not necessarily. So, I
don't really like to pay too much
attention to AVD and CTR. I look at
views and I look at retention curves.
The reason why views don't really lie.
They're what you would call a
comprehensive metric because everything
goes into views, right? The click, the
watch, the satisfaction, all that goes
into the view count you see. [snorts]
So,
>> because it's feeding the algorithm.
>> Yeah.
>> So, views don't lie for the most part.
So, I'll look at views. And then the
other thing I'll look at is retention
curves. So the actual curve because that
teaches me where people are dropping
off, where I'm losing people. So I have
been a little bit of a psycho when it
comes to retention curves, but I have
studied like thousands if not tens of
thousands of retention curves across
multiple niches and you start to see the
patterns of like what causes people to
leave? What causes people to drop off?
When you say this, you know, 5% people
leave or 2% people leave. Why is that?
So when I was talking to bigger beginner
creators, even even like bigger
creators, I'm like, look at your views
and look at your retention curves.
Understand which video is working
better. Focus on those. Understand the
patterns of your your viewership as
well. Like you know, if you change a
title thumbnail, like I don't really
care about the CTR. I care about to
delete to more views, right? It's like
if I created a different sign for my
lemonade stand, if everything else was a
control, if it was in Times Square New
York and it was held as a control, okay,
then I can make measure the conversion
rate change. But if I change the sign,
but then some of the time I'm in outside
my front door at my house and some of
the time I'm in Time Square, New York,
it's hard to like measure whether it's a
sign or whether it's something else.
Views is pretty consistent. So views and
retention curve. And retention the
interesting thing about retention curve
is, you know, you could have a retention
curve on a video that has a million
views and then that video could get 10
million more views. The retention curve
will be lower because as you go to a
broader audience, generally engagement
drops and people are less engaged in the
video. So,
>> because they're finding net new
audiences that are less likely to click
your video. They're just trying to grow
it as much as possible.
>> Exactly. Exactly. So, they're less
likely to watch your video, but that
doesn't mean that the video is less
interesting. It's just like, you know,
naturally like, you know, the same same
way that like if you listen to a band
you've never heard before, you're less
likely to listen for as long as like
your favorite artist, right? It's like
the same thing, right? So, what happens
though that's interesting is let's say
the retention curve will drop. We can
actually show I could send you a really
cool visual which summarizes this. the
retention curve could drop quite
considerably down after 10 million
views, but the behaviors are still
pretty similar. So if if you know core
viewers left at this moment, new viewers
are probably still going to leave at
that same moment or at a similar moment.
Like the the actual behavior stays
pretty consistent between audiences like
universally people might find this thing
funny or not that funny. Or if I say in
a video at the end of the day, whether
you're a new viewer, a core viewer, a
casual viewer, most people determine
that as ending language, as conclusion
language at the end of the day. So if I
just said there like look at the end of
the day this was a great podcast cut
this out if I said that like people are
going to be subconsciously listening on
their you know iPhones iPads on their
TVs and be like oh it's finishing now go
right so universally that leads to drops
guys it's Mark quick break is one of the
sharpest minds on YouTube strategy today
and he has given us so much free game in
this episode so I put together a
playbook that distills all of his
systems and frameworks into one free PDF
link below down in the description.
Enjoy the rest of the episode. So,
prepackaging idea, title, thumbnail.
Taking a look back from a macro
perspective, the two big things are
views and retention. Let's go deep into
retention. Now, I feel like we should
start with the intro because again, good
title, good thumbnail, people click, and
then the beginning. I mean, this is I
don't even want to show it. Maybe we'll
pop it up just so we can laugh at me.
Like, our first couple episodes, the
intro was slow. I'm talking about
myself. It has no context. Absolutely
terrible and it's a it's a micrometric,
but the average view duration was very
very low. So, I'd love to hear from you
like what are those kind of rules on the
intro to get people to stay along and
buy yourself a chance to kind of feed
the algorithm?
>> 100%. So, interestingly, I mentioned
earlier my parents are both writers and
I think I have probably ghost written
10,000 intros
in my career for my own channels for
other channels. And still today, like I
have a whole team. I'm technically the
CEO. I'm supposed to be just signing
business and, you know, leading the
company. I still ghost write intros for
our clients all the time. Let it go,
baby.
>> I just love it. It's It's like my
favorite thing. And I just love like how
you get this like the thing I didn't
like about writing is I I always love
writing stories and essays and you know
I wanted to be a journalist at some
point. Very hard to get your kind of
like you know feedback immediately on is
this good or not? Like whereas with
intros I can be like okay I tried this
intro people didn't like it they left
you know I can see exactly where they
left in the retention curve. So I love
writing intros. My formula it's going to
be different to other people's formulas.
The thing about intros is ultimately all
that matters is can you hold people on
the video. There's some principles that
are just general. So like one principle
that general to me is like generally it
shouldn't be that long. An intro
probably should be under 45 seconds. You
know, sometimes you can go a bit longer,
but like most of the best performing
intros on YouTube, they're under 45
seconds, right? They use simple
language. They focus on intrigue and
like getting people like bought into the
video and leading with proof points and
these different things. But the actual
format I use is three steps. Number one,
deliver on the promise. So, I love this
idea of thinking of your title thumbnail
as a promise. That's what it is, right?
You're basically telling people, I
promise you, I'm going to give you this,
right? What is so obviously a mistake
people make is they make a big promise
with the title out and then in the first
10 seconds of their intro, they do not
reaffirm that. They do not like deliver
on it at all. So, if you make a promise
that you're going to see the world's
fastest camera drone versus an F1 car
and you start the video and you don't
see a drone or an F1 car, you're like,
I'm gone. And genuinely, I have seen
videos on YouTube where in the first 10%
or first 10 seconds of a video, 60% 70%
of viewers have left. And it's like 10
seconds, not like a minute in, 10
seconds, you have now you only have 30
or 40% of viewers left after the first
10 seconds. And it nearly always is
because you click the video and you're
just not getting what you came for. And
I'm sure people watching this can can
relate to this and experience how
frustrating it is when you click on a
video and you're like, I came for this
and it just feels like I've been baited
into something completely different and
it doesn't make any sense. So delivering
on the promise, you can do that visually
or verbally, you know, like you could
visually show an F1 car and a drone or
you could verbally say that that's
coming. I think the visual is a lot
stronger in this example. Let's say for
our episode, you might make a certain
claim in the title about like what this
episode's titled around. Just want to
make sure those first 10 seconds I'm
saying something to that effect or
saying something similar or you're
saying something similar to that effect.
So deliver on the promise is number one
for me. Make sure they make they made
the right decision. I want to kind of
say like I've got someone with the
click. I want to grab them and be like
you made the right choice. Trust me.
Trust me. Look at this. You made the
right choice. That's my first step.
Number two is create intrigue. Very
basic, very generic. But your intro is
not just about statements. And this is a
big mistake people make is they they
sometimes be they're they're sometimes
too statement focused. So they kind of
go like, you know, they'll just be like,
in this video we're going to cover this,
this, this, and this. Okay, let's go. I
was like, okay, you know, I guess it's
pragmatic, but it's not creating much
interest. I want to hear things like,
you know, in this video we're going to
cover this and how it leads to this, and
we're even going to break down the, you
know, I want to hear that kind of
interestbased language. So, I'm always
looking for like what what are the
little hooks, curiosity gaps. I like to
think of my intro as just opening up all
these little hooks in the viewer's mind
where they're like, I have to keep
watching to hear these things answered
throughout the video. So, that to me is
the second most important thing. And on
that point as well, I like to do that in
the least amount of context as possible.
So, big problem people do is they
overexlain in their intros. They put too
much in. This is probably what you did
at the start, right? You put too much
information. You thought you had to
introduce the guest too much. you to
like build all this stuff up and it's
like try to explain that in the in the
least amount of time as possible. So
like only necessary context in that
section. So create interest with the
least amount of words possible
basically. And I always like to use this
example of like if you do look at like I
know we're using him quite a lot in this
episode. If you look at like a genius
like Mr. Beast in his videos technically
there's so much happening in his videos.
What if you gave that to an amateur or
just like a let's say a good YouTuber,
they would feel the need to explain
everything that's happening like, "Oh,
there's this FBI agent. He used to work
for the FBI for 20 years. His name is
John and he's going to be chasing me for
24 hours, and if he can capture me, he
gets to keep this bag of money. If he
doesn't," and you know, all this
explanation, that's what most people do.
He's just like, "This is an FBI agent.
He's got 24 hours to catch me, go." You
know, like it's it's like you don't need
to say his name now. You can drip feed
context. You can put context in later.
This idea drip feeding context I think
is really interesting which is like you
know what's the most necessary context
to make someone understand the video and
create intrigue for them and then the
rest of the context I mean you can put
that later like you know people maybe
didn't know need to know in this intro
that I worked for exactly this person or
that I own this company or that my dog
went viral but we can we can you know
drip that in as we go. And then my third
step of a a great intro is seamless
flow. So, I I said this thing a while
ago, which is like the best intro
doesn't feel like an intro. It just
feels like the video started. So, yes,
like, you know, an intro reel or like a
a sort of highlights of of the
conversation or clips if it's a podcast,
that can be great. That can work really
well, but it should feel like it just
seamlessly flows into the start of the
story line, right? If I sort of say to
you like, "We're going to do this thing.
It's going to be great. Um, anyway, uh,
let's get into it. Okay, we're into the
thing." Right? That's a very like choppy
start to the video. Like it doesn't flow
very well. If I said and said, "We're
going to do this thing. It's going to be
great and we're going to start with this
and then the video starts, right? And
we're going to start." That's the
connecting sentence that makes it flow.
So, I always look for those seamless
flows. And if you look at the great
intros on YouTube, you're almost like
watching the intro and then it's like,
"Oh [__] the video started." And it's
great. So, that's that's my formula.
>> Yeah. I think what's underrated and I
actually do this before I do the actual
intro is that first bridging sentence.
So I'll do the social proofing. It'll be
two, three sentences. I'll say, you
know, the 50 billion views, the Eagles,
Red Bulls, Mr. Beast, etc. But then
what's that first sentence because
that's where I know like the meat of the
conversation is going to go and then I
actually do that after the fact. What's
your thoughts on the trailer that we
have first? So we have like a 45se
second highlight sizzle trailer and then
like a 105 second intro and then the
first question. What's your thoughts on
that? Dice us up. This may or may not
make it. Dice this up, baby.
>> That trailer takes a long time.
>> Yeah. So, I hate the word trailer. So, I
I know that technically is what it is,
but like that
>> it's a [__] movie. That's what it is.
>> Yeah.
>> That that gives me because like I think
a lot of people for a lot of people
that's a terrible idea.
>> Yeah.
>> I think for you it can work because the
production level is insane. And I think
half like the unique selling point here
is you get great people. You know, I'm
not I'm just going to blow smoke up your
ass for a second, but like I've never
gone on a podcast that's prepared me as
much for it and like gone through as
much stuff. So like you you have all
this like amazing value. You've got
beautiful visuals. You've got all this
sort of stuff. So I think like that in a
way is delivering on the promise and
it's like showcasing what's great about
the conversation and it's not like your
intro real is like I don't know like
today we sat down with Patty Galloway
but you know that to me is like get rid
of that right but if it's like an actual
sizzler where it's like good
conversations that's more the diary of a
CEO approach. I can't critique it. The
biggest podcast in the world does that.
Like Diary of a CEO does that. On the
flip side, you know, a podcast like
Modern Wisdom, Chris Williamson, who's
also one of the biggest podcasts in the
world, he'll quite often just start his
podcast with just a question just like,
"So, what do you think about this?" And
it just starts, right? So, I think
you've got competing like different ends
of the spectrum of different ways to
start things. I think for now, I think
the trailer makes sense for you. As you
grow, you might actually transition to
something a bit shorter. Ironically, uh,
we live kind of somewhere in between the
Darco and Chris Williamson where I
completely agree like while all these
principles and frameworks out there,
everybody listening, you have to take it
with a grain of salt and like use common
sense. That's how we look at it is we
think like one of our modes is obviously
the production value. So, we have the
trailer, but at the same time, I want to
respect the audience's time and then
like we get into it right away. We don't
like schmuck around in the beginning. We
were right into it, I don't know, in
like 30 seconds. So, you got to really
just find what works for you. And as far
as like the algorithm goes, is there
anything else that people need to know
outside of like when you upload a video,
obviously the first hour is very
important when you want to retain
people. Is there anything else that
people should know from a retention
perspective on like timing?
>> So the interesting thing about retention
to me is like the videos that hold
people for a long time and leave them
really satisfied are usually the videos
that become the most evergreen. So that
I think the biggest when I look at the
different algorithms and then I look at
YouTube I think YouTube's biggest
strength is the fact it's an evergreen
algorithm. Like you if I go into my
YouTube feed right now and I pull it up
I guarantee you I see a video from 6
months ago from 2 years ago from 3 days
ago from 2 hours ago from 8 years ago.
Like it is this kind of just platform of
distribution. And it's kind of funny
like people go like oh YouTube are
prioritizing new videos or are they
prioritizing old videos? All these
things. It's like they're prioritizing
whatever the [__] people will click on.
Like if they're going to click on a
video from eight years ago, they're
going to show videos from eight years
ago. I always like this idea, which is
funny, which is like if everyone
tomorrow only clicked videos that were 6
hours long. Let's say the whole world,
we only clicked videos that were 6 hours
long and were like a black screen and
just said video one at the top. That's
all that would be displayed on YouTube.
Like they are reflecting human behavior.
Like the algorithm, I know people like
to think it's like cur like YouTube
putting their finger on the scale and
curating a certain thing. Look, we can
get into we won't get into like that
sort of stuff, but like there is some
things that they create. They're like,
"Okay, we don't want this kind of
content or we don't want like really
violent content or whatever." But after
that, it's the wild west. It's like
whatever gets the most clicks and
watches and satisfies people will be at
the top of the platform. Great example
of this would be like, I'm kind of going
on a tangent, but this is fun. Great
example of this would be TV, right? So
TV has become this really powerful
device type for YouTube. It's crazy. I
can actually send you a graph about this
which is wild but like even five or 6
years ago only about 20% 15 20% of our
clients traffic was from TV. That number
today is like 50 60%. like in just five
years. So, we're playing in this
completely different game, right? And
what's interesting is like I heard
someone a really smart person I respect
say like, "Oh, YouTube are prioritizing
longer videos cuz they do better on TV,
right?" Which I guess technically is not
incorrect, but the way I think the way
the reason I bring this up as a point is
really important is because everyone
goes like, "Oh, yeah, like YouTube are
just trying to make people watch longer
like all this sort of stuff. They're
prioritizing longer videos." Like longer
videos do better on TV because YouTube
are trying to make them do better on TV.
It's like, do you know why longer videos
are doing better on TV? Cuz people want
to watch longer videos on TV. If you're
sitting down and you're like, I'm going
to pick a video and you see a 4-minute
video. I don't know if anyone relates to
this. Like, but like if I see a 4-minute
video, I'm like, I don't want to watch
that on my TV. I have to put it on and
then it's going to be finished right
away. It's like, I want to watch a
30-minute video on my TV, right? So,
it's not a case of YouTube prioritizing
longer videos. It's a case of the
audience telling YouTube, look, we
prefer longer videos on TV. So, what
gets promoted on on TV? Longer videos.
If you open up your TV right now, you'll
see longer videos than if you open up
your mobile. So the device type itself
informs and you know the YouTube
algorithm is just so vast, but it can
just be described with this simple fact
which is for the most part it is always
right behind the audience. Whatever way
the audience is going, if everyone
tomorrow decided we're going to watch
sixinute videos with no audio, that's
what will get promoted. That is so
mind-blowing because on my TV I've never
ever watched shorts and I'm thinking
right now it's all long form because
that's the intent with that medium. And
kind of riffing off what you just said,
I definitely think that the only thing
that's kind of part of the algo is, you
know, you always hear that like they're
giving small creators like a chance.
Maybe they are, maybe they do do that,
but then it ultimately comes down to
okay, we'll give you the chance that
small pool, but if you don't get the
clicks and the watches, then you're dead
to them. Yeah.
>> So, it's really just comes down to
clicks and views. That's what it always
comes down to.
>> And it's it's just a beautiful game
where it's like it is it is almost like
pure meritocracy. It's like if you are a
small creator and you make a better
video than me and my clients, you will
get more views. The difficulty would be
like, well, at the highest level, people
on YouTube right now have these big
budgets, these big teams. They have, you
know, people like, you know, even hiring
us is not cheap, right? Like, and they
have, you know, all these things that
they have behind them. But if you can
make a better video than us, you will
get more views than us. And the good
thing about being earlier in the stage
as well is just like in business, right?
Why? Look, Google, Microsoft, you know,
the fang, all these huge companies.
Technically, they're the biggest
companies in the world. They're all
trillion dollar market caps. Still,
every year there's startups getting
acquired. There's huge startups being
built, you know, that come out of
nowhere. And it's because when you get
big, it becomes harder to experiment and
move. So smaller creators or or people
starting out have the advantage of
flexibility and having an audience that
they can't disappoint, you know, or or
they Yeah. Like they having an audience
that they don't really have to risk at
that point. So there is this like fun
thing where like as a small creator,
yes, you're competing with big creators
on on a lot of fronts. Also, we can get
into this, but I feel like a lot of the
fronts that typically were gatekeepers
are dissolving with AI. It's like, oh,
like, oh, the big creators have all
these editors and graphics that I can't
have. AI's coming in and helping you
with that, right? Right? So, as a small
creator, like you're able to be more
flexible and agile and and it is just a
pure competition. If you can make a
better video than me, you'll get more
views than me.
>> This goes back to the most important
skill to have in 2026 to be able to go
viral because ultimately Yago doesn't
lie. It's going to feed the views. We
could spend all day going on these kind
of storytelling structures. That's the
next thing that I want to really jump
into. We're just going to put a bunch of
them below in a PDF, guys, because I
want to keep going here. I think the big
thing to understand on the storytelling
is just a good storytelling structure is
is basically useless without stakes. So
I'd love for you to just kind of walk
through how people should be filtering
in their brain incorporating stakes into
their whole entire kind of a toz
playbook and making the videos.
>> Yeah, such a good question. I think the
thing is like yeah, you're right. You
could have a great you could follow all
the rules. You could have a great
structure, great storytelling format,
all these things. If people don't care
enough to be invested in the video, like
they're just not going to watch it. It
just doesn't matter. So, like, if I
said, let's just like use like a live
demo of this. Like, if I let's just say
I crunch up this paper into like a I'm
actually going to do this with this.
>> Yeah.
If I crunch this up into a ball and like
let's just say there's a bin. There's a
trash can off camera and I just go, I'm
gonna throw this into the trash can. So,
you're probably like, "Okay, cool." If I
said, "I'm gonna throw this into the
trash can." And your camera guy off
camera here. He said there's no way I
can do it. He thinks there's no shot I
can do this.
>> I'll go next.
>> You're a bit more invested, right?
>> And then if you throw in the trash can
and get it in,
>> I'm going to give Tiger a million
dollars.
>> I better [__] get it in.
>> And you could just keep going more and
more and more.
>> Yeah.
>> Maybe I'll give Tiger a million dollars
and punch Jake in the face.
>> If you get it in and then everybody's
just, is he going to get it in? Is he
not going to get it in? Are you going to
give him the money? Are you gonna show
us punching Jake in the face?
>> 100% stakes. Yeah. Right. And it's like
over overly like almost like facitious
level stakes there, but like that is
that is human interest, right? It's like
>> people
>> don't care unless you make them care and
like you know that could be it could be
an enemy to overcome. The first one I
used was an enemy, right? Like he
doesn't think I can do it, right? Like
that's like such a classic human
psychology thing. Like you're like I'm
about to run a marathon, you know? Okay,
I'm about to run a marathon and my
ex-husband divorced me because he said I
couldn't get fit. I'm way more invested
in now. You know, it's like that's where
you create that that feeling and that
stake. So, it could be a time limit. It
could be like a reward. It could be a
punishment. It could even just be like
the kind of FOMO of missing out. Like,
you know, earlier in this episode, we
gave an example of like buying the new
iPhone, don't buy the wrong one or like
don't waste your money. Like, that feels
like a stake. It's like I don't want to
waste my money on the wrong iPhone.
Like, you've got to like you can't just
be pure pragmatic. You've got to think
like why does someone care about this
thing?
>> And can anybody hypothetically
manufacture stakes in videos?
>> Yes, you just got to you got to
understand when stakes matter, right?
Like if I am making you a video saying
here's how to let's just say the video
I'm making is how to optimize your
investment portfolio, right? And I'm
like, okay, so today I'm going to make
make a video where I break down the the
most bulletproof investment portfolio.
It's really important you pay attention
because if you don't listen to this, I
have someone in another room who's going
to break down the door and put slime
over my head. So, you got to keep
watching. You know, if I if I can't
explain this to you in 10 minutes, I'm
going to get slimed.
I mean, that's just bizarre. It's like,
I came to you for information. I don't
care about you getting slimed. Who are
you? That's weird. What the hell? Like,
what's going on here? If you said
instead, I'm going to break down the
most bulletproof investment portfolio
for you. And this is so important to get
right because the difference between
this portfolio and the one that the
average person picks is over $3 million
in retirement. It's like well that's a
stake because it feels like a cost if I
don't understand the information. So
it's about like understanding what's the
right stake for the video, right? Like
it's not always like a goofy actionbased
stake. It can also be just like a what's
the cost of not paying attention.
>> Guys, we're going to pop down below.
This PDF is going to be jam-packed with
principles, frameworks, examples, all
the different ways to create stakes. We
talked about a couple. We're going to
put all of them down below. I want to
open up and talk more about just, you
know, you've been in this I mean, when
have you been in this space since you
were 10 years old?
>> Yeah, I turned 30 this year.
>> Okay. So, Patty's been in the space for
20 years. He's 30 years old. He has been
in the space for 66% of his life at only
30 years old. I want to just We have a
lot of operators listening right here.
So, I kind of want to get into how
should brands look at YouTube? What does
the future of YouTube look like? So, I
guess let's just first start with like
what is the biggest mistake that you
think that operators are doing when
they're entering YouTube?
>> I would say having a YouTube channel to
begin with.
So, here's my my sort of like scorched
earth take on it, which is like don't
have a [__] YouTube channel unless
you're willing to put in the time and
effort to grow it. And as an operator,
like you're probably very busy on a lot
of things. So, you've got to really
understand if this is like the thing for
you. And it's it's like you know what's
going to drive business for you. I am
very bullish on company channels and
brand channels. But I think the worst
thing is when it's halfass and you like
you know when I go on my my rants you
know when I have a few drinks with me
and I start ranting I'll start pointing
out like these brand channels and I'm
like what is the point of that? Like you
know you there's this huge brand that's
worth half a billion half a trillion
dollars and they're just posting like
corporate training video weird stuff on
their YouTube channel and it's just
garbage. I'll call out OpenAI. Cool
company, right? Awesome company. I
looked at their YouTube channel the
other day. I'm like this is what's the
point of this? Like it's just sort of
hosting ads. It's just a dumping ground
of like random things and that's a cool
new company with like fresh smart people
all over it. And like I in their case, I
think it's almost better for them just
to have like a an ad account and not
even have a YouTube channel if they're
going to do that. So I think it's like
my my sort of score take is you probably
shouldn't have a channel unless you're
willing to put in the effort to do it.
And then I think for the most part it's
like you either need to like get really
good at the skill which I think is super
valuable. Like if if you're as a
founder, as an operator, if you're able
to figure out the skill of like what
sells attention, what gains attention,
as we've said, I think it's one of the
most valuable skills in the world. But
the other thing which I see a lot of
people do, a lot of entrepreneurs do is
just find the strategist. Find the
person that can come in and be kind of
like the creative director for your
YouTube channel, for your brand. You
know, a lot of these big business
creators right now, you see them in
front of the camera, but there's someone
behind them. There's like a 22-year-old
that's there and just lives and breathes
content and they're growing it, you
know, themselves. Like I have a friend
and probably Greg from Austin from
Bloom,
>> Uncle Greg, that episode will be up by
now. We'll pop that up.
>> Awesome. So Greg, he's a buddy of mine.
like you know he's got a guy brilliant
creative guy that's just behind the
scenes working on him to figure out the
YouTube channel with him and it's like I
think bringing someone like that in is
is super valuable but yeah the YouTube
can be so powerful for business but it
has to be done right like we we're with
our clients like the the clients we talk
about like we've worked with you know
obviously the Red Bull we've worked with
Philadelphia Eagles Yeti car companies
we even worked with like the academy
like the Oscars you know so many
different companies and like the ones
that crush it take it seriously like
they really go for it.
>> I think like my and again I'm not
welcoming more competition in the space.
You guys can have fun. You can listen or
not listen. But I think what's awesome
about YouTube and it kind of plays to
the whole thesis of this video is it is
of all the platforms and all the skills.
I'm talking about long form YouTube. It
is the most transferable skill that
gives you the most impact under the
notion that if you think about like
communication, whether it be photo,
whether it be video, whether it be
writing, like video is the holy grail
because that can be you can take
screenshots, it could be photo, you can
transcript it, it can be words and then
you think long form versus short form.
Long form can be diced up into short
form. And then just the evergreen nature
of it. I mean, bro, I'll actually pop
her up. Uh, she actually lives in
Austin. Her name is Kao. I might have to
pay her an extra bag of money for this.
She We gave her art like five, six,
seven years ago and she did like a
random UTM link. Bro, it still gets
sales. Like people don't understand like
the evergreen nature where a it could
just hit the algorithm. Maybe you redo
the thumbnail or B maybe someone goes
down a rabbit hole and looks through
your whole channel and they find, you
know, an outlier video from six years
ago because they're a diehard fan. They
see a brand they like in an ad read and
they buy it. Like it is. There's no
other platform that is evergreen like
this. It's not even close.
>> You're creating real estate.
>> Well, it it's insane. And I just I I you
know, we were talking, you know, off
camera before this. It's just like I
don't know why. Maybe because like CMOs
need to be held to numbers and there
needs to be like attribution tied to it.
But like if you have money and you have
the ability to be patient for quite
frankly, if you're not an idiot, let's
just call it 18 months. We're not even
18 months into this podcast, bro. We're
less than 18 months in.
>> Yeah.
>> And you just
get better incrementally. Get a little
bit more views, learn a little something
from each video. It's undefeated. One of
my biggest regrets with Iconic is we had
a web series and we stopped doing it and
we had momentum in 2016 2017. If we were
still doing that now,
>> yeah,
>> it would be absolutely [__] crazy.
and and like think about you know these
companies like I I reference like an
open AI claw these cool new companies
but like I think the biggest problem
some of those companies face is like
sentiment you know it's like YouTube
gives you a platform where you can
control narrative it's where you can
present the great things you're doing
like when I talk to sometimes these I'm
sure you feel the same conversation like
these CMOs CEOs of these big brands and
companies they're always like oh people
just don't understand like how much cool
stuff we're doing and all this sort of
stuff and like you could have a YouTube
channel and just control the
conversation and show the world like
what is cool that you're doing. Like I
always say like this is a crazy stat but
like the second biggest purchase in
America makes is a car right after
they're home. Generally 90% of purchase
decisions around cars are now primarily
made on YouTube.
>> Wow.
>> People their second biggest purchase
it's not the dealer. It's not the advert
on the TV. It's not reading it in the
paper. It's not going onto the website.
It's watching the car videos on YouTube
and being like is the new BMW X5 better
than the previous gen or whatever. And
it's like it's one of those things where
it sounds crazy to say but then you
think about it. Like, yeah, obviously if
if I was like to you, buy you need to
buy a new car tomorrow. First place
you'd probably go is like, okay, let me
look at YouTube and see some comparison
videos or whatnot. And it's like the
biggest second biggest purchase
Americans make is being made on YouTube.
Like every car channel should be really
making great YouTube videos in my
opinion because they get to first look
at their cars. They get to control the
conversation. They get to showcase the
videos, you know, instead of like, you
know, that those views just going
somewhere else. So I am so bullish on
companies that have the resources and
time to commit to YouTube for 24 months
and just say let's make great videos on
YouTube and that's what we try to do
with our clients. We're just like let's
make great videos.
>> That's a great reference cars because I
mean if you think about the CAC how much
it costs and like you're underwriting
like paying the salespeople, you know,
paying the dealership and then the LTV.
Someone buys one Honda, they're probably
going to be a Honda for life. They're
going to buy three, four, five Hondas.
That is insane. That's a that that's a
great analogy. If a brand has a $100,000
to spend on YouTube, I would imagine
that's a lot of people out here
listening. Where do you think they
start?
>> I think for $100,000 you hire me 10
years ago.
I think you look for a creative person
who understands YouTube generally. And
here's the thing, it's like I think when
people try to make this hire, they often
like look for like, you know, someone
who is, you know, traditionally trained
or is really good at this thing or that
thing. It's like, no, I'm actually
looking for YouTubers. Like, if I was a
brand, I would be like, okay, let's just
say I'm a brand and I'm in like the
beverage space, right? I would look and
just see like, is there any like cool
creators out there that already making
content that's pretty good? Like one of
my friends is starting this coffee shop
in Austin and he's just like showing me
this this guy and he's like, oh, this
guy said he would run my social media
for me, run my YouTube for me. And I'm
like, has he ever done YouTube before?
Has he ever grown anything? And he's
like, no. But he's like, look at how
cool he can make stuff look. And I'm
like, I don't care. you can find someone
that's not making any money on YouTube,
but is making kind of interesting stuff
and is, you know, maybe getting a few
thousand views a video and it's like,
"Oh, do you want to come work for me for
80,000 a year, 100,000 a year?" So, I
think probably with that budget, like if
I if I didn't want to figure it out
myself, I would try to hire that person
and I would look at people already doing
it and just say, "Come full time with me
and let's make something on the channel
together." if I want to like really
invest into myself to learn and get the
skills I think you just got to start
looking at yourself as like this is
going to be a large commitment like you
said yourself like you know it's 18 24
months and you know but if you master it
it's like now every company you ever
start you have a skill that you can
build an audience around your product
and around around what you're doing
>> and like I said I think having the skill
of YouTube basically lends itself to all
their platforms but you can't reverse it
like if you're really good at Twitter
guys that does not mean that you're
going to be really good at YouTube. So
yeah, I would lead with someone being
good at YouTube. What do you think they
should prioritize first? So like if
somebody starts a channel, what should
they prioritize first
>> in terms of hire?
>> No, they hire someone and then they
start they they press go. What should
they be prioritizing?
>> I I think at the start it's just about
like there's this idea that I love which
is the YouTube pendulum idea that I came
up with a few years ago. And it's this
idea that like the pendulum kind of
shifts depending on what stage of the
journey you're in. And I can send you
the graphic so we can share it. But the
idea basically is like at the start
you're kind of at the far left of the
pendulum. And what that means is your
videos just need to be watchable. So for
the first start, like it sounds so
basic, but you just need to make a video
that someone can watch. Like it doesn't
matter if it's good. It doesn't matter
if it gets a,000 views, 100,000 views,
you just need to be able to make a video
that like the audio isn't isn't
terrible. The picture isn't terrible.
Like it's it's it looks okay, right? And
like it's funny like I'm sort of
laughing about it but like you know I
looked at a $400 billion dollar publicly
listed brand and their YouTube channel
was literally not watchable. Their audio
was terrible. I was like you cannot
watch this. So like it doesn't matter
anything else like you can't watch this.
So in the pendulum at the start it's
like video quality is the most important
thing to focus on. Like just make your
videos watchable. So step one is like
get the video quality there. Then the
pendulum starts to shift over towards
ideas and packaging. So once you have
like a video let's say you go from like
a video that's barely watchable to now
okay your video's okay. good like you
can make a rough video. Now the pendulum
switches over to like the packaging game
in my opinion and then the focus of
course you're working on everything all
the time but the focus becomes more on
title on thumbnail on idea. So at that
point if you're if you're in this
position I think it's about like okay
like we've got to a point where we can
make something look okay now let's see
what are the best videos in the space
talk through our ideation framework we
talked about like look at the top
performers go and make the top 20 with
your own twist on them like start making
these ideas and thinking really about
idea and packaging once you master idea
and packaging which by the way takes a
very long time like I would say I still
haven't mastered it even though I think
I'm really good then the pendulum starts
to shift back again towards video
quality and then It's like, okay, can we
level up the production even further?
Can we like shoot with 4K cameras? Can
we like add like extra angles and shots
and stuff like that? But the interesting
thing is when a lot of like brands or
operators think about YouTube, they just
think of like how can I make it look
better? How can I make it look better?
How can I make it look better? And then
everything is just about how can I make
it look better? And it's not about
what's the idea, the title, the
thumbnail, the story. So there is that
pendulum effect.
>> Yeah. I would say another thing too just
my personal opinion is I've said it
before I think I said in the Samir
episode is just ideation prepackaging
production post-production and then the
last part is how do you find creative
ways to amplify the distribution and
further feed the algorithm because
obviously you can do the the
prepackaging stuff and and and feed the
algorithm but what are even like
creative ways that you can get outside
traffic to come in and watch the video
and just fuel the fire. I want to tie
this up. So, what did Red Bull get
right? Cuz you've been with them for a
couple years and their views are 10,
20x. What did they get right that
everybody else is getting wrong?
>> So, I think you know what's interesting
about Redbull is like Red Bull have
always been good at content like
historically. So, some even when I bring
them up as a case study, people are just
like it's Rebel. They were always
getting views. I'm like, well, you know,
back when we signed them, they were
doing 400 500,000 views a video. Now
they're doing eight or nine million. So,
you're right. Like, it's it's a 10 20x.
But I think what they did right was,
this will sound a little maybe the first
arrogant thing I've said on the podcast,
but I think they were willing to listen
to me and to creators and not think
that, you know, they themselves, you
know, had all the answers. Like they
Rebel have like some really smart
YouTube people in there. But of course,
it's a huge company, but they really
gave a lot of reigns to the YouTube team
that they have there and then to to my
team and just let us kind of like make
it happen. And I will give so much
credit to the brand because I know I
know how easy it is when you have a big
company for everyone to get involved and
start like putting their fingers in it
and like messing around with it and
stuff, but like they they've always been
very good about like, okay, what do we
need to do? Like we'll make it happen.
So I think they did that right. And I
think from one thing they just deserve
huge credit for was just the foresight
of like 5 years ago all these brands
were like, "Oh, we just need to make a
documentary that gets like on a Netflix
show or like we need to do this or
that." And Red Bull were just like
YouTube is it. You know, YouTube is the
premium platform for video, right? And
it's like five years ago, maybe you
wouldn't have said that. Today, it's
like, well, the average YouTube video is
like 15 to 20 minutes, 30 minutes.
That's kind of like TV, huh? And then
it's like, now they're really high
production. Now, they're being watched
on TV. 60 70% of traffic is coming from
TV for some channels. And it's like
YouTube is is the premium place to have
your own content. And I think they saw
that before most people.
>> Sounds practical. Hire experts and
empower them. How do they look at ROI?
How do they like evaluate like your
partnership? Is it views?
>> So, when we first started it was it was
views. It was like a part of my my deal
would would have been on like a certain
growth target and growing to a certain
number. But I think it's kind of like at
at a certain scale for a brand like
that. It's kind of the same reason of
how do they how do they calculate ROI on
their F1 team or on their like soccer
teams. It's like I think the best way
you calculate ROI for a Red Rebel or the
best way you see the value for Redbull
is the fact that when you make an ad,
it's 10 seconds, it's 15 seconds, it's
20 seconds, whatever it is, and people
aren't really engaged. When you make a
video that gets 20 million views, like
the one that I just scrunched up in this
ball, or 30 million views, it is 30
million people that watch for 5 minutes
or 10 minutes. Like, where else can you
buy that? Like if I if I just sort of
said with money buy 30 million people
watching 10 minutes plus of a 20inut
video that's 10 minutes of them spending
time with you. Where else can you buy
that?
>> Yeah. I mean if you back into the CPMs
then again however much they're paying
you is probably not enough if you if you
back into the millions and millions of
views quite frankly. Pretty crazy. So
for everybody out there listening I
think it's pretty pretty clear. We're
going to repop up that pendulum. I think
the pendulum is great. It's start with
something. and get the technical down,
the audio, the video, and then basically
listen to this podcast three, four,
five, six, 10 times, download the PDF,
implement all the things that we talked
about, and then just swing back and
forth. I'd be remiss if we didn't talk
about AI. So, I'd love to just know how
do you integrate AI into your content,
your client's content? How do you see
AI?
>> So, I think I'm I'm one of those people
that's like kind of bullish and bearish
at the same time, which is like, and I'm
I'm sure people relate to this, which is
like you see some people say, "I'm using
AI for everything. It's great. It's
amazing. It's it's completely
transformed my content workflow. It's
it's everything. And then I see some
people and they're like, "Yeah, I'm not
using it at all." And I see both those
people winning. Like, you know, so I'm
It's quite hard to sometimes get through
the noise. We're using AI a lot in
pre-production. So when I said that 500
ideas, like it's amazing how useful AI
is in ideation. So, for example, like
Claude has a plugin where you can
connect the platforms like Vid IQ. I
think one of 10 might have that
connection yet. And you can connect it
through Claude and then actually talk to
Claude about outliers. Be like, "Okay,
I'm in the fitness niche. Go find the
top 20 most viewed videos in the last
365 days that are focused on this
specific topic and then let's talk about
them, brainstorm around them together."
So we'll use claude and and gemini but
mainly claude a lot in the ideation
process right now. We use Gemini a lot
for image generation for thumbnails for
even just for like concepts for
thumbnail concepts. So we'll use Gemini
a lot in that in that sense. And then
honestly the one area I'm I'm curious
what you think about this, but the one
area we have not been able to like
successfully use AI is still writing
good content. Like we we get it like 80%
of the way there, but I think the 20% is
always still human. It's still like, you
know, the person getting on top. So
yeah, we'll use it a lot in
pre-production, but not as much in post
and and not as much in the in the
writing of content. Yeah, obviously I
use it for like outlines, but from a
Yeah, I don't use it for anything from a
writing perspective, but I have yet to
not be overly obsessed on the
pre-production side and make sure that
I'm putting in the time to really know
the guest. I almost am scared, quite
frankly, to just solely rely on AI in
the pre-production where my team
probably at this point is probably
[__] frustrated that like I need to
put in X amount of time on
pre-production or I don't feel
comfortable walking onto this set that
the product is going to be at the level
that it needs to be at. So there's
certain things with AI will never take
place with the human. I also just want
to touch on something that you said and
guys, we're going to link it down below
and I'm going to pop it up right now.
The episode's going to be out. What
Patty was talking about, they're called
MCPs and they're basically connectors
where you can get data from a third
party source and bring it into Claude
and ask a question. So we did an episode
with a guy named Remy, absolute 21, 22y
old [__] ninja. We went through all
of this and yeah, it could help you all
of these questions, you know, outliers
for titles, thumbnails, ideas, all of
that stuff. It could take the raw data
from the third party platforms and give
you kind of dialed in ideas. Huge
[__] fan of the MCP. Yep. Huge, huge
fan. All right, so I want to round the
corner before we get to Quick Strag. I
want to talk about the next decade.
Obviously, we're talking about
principles and frameworks that apply to
any platform, but YouTube is kind of the
big one that I think both of us are
championing. Get on YouTube. Where does
YouTube go in the next 10 years? Where
do you think it goes? I am unbelievably
bullish on YouTube to the point where
it's almost concerning to people around
me who aren't because I have two main
companies both focused on YouTube. Most
of my investments are in YouTube focused
companies. My biggest like individual
stock is Google. Like I am just like so
bullish on YouTube as a whole. And I
have been that way for the last 10 years
pretty much. Like I remember arguing
with people. I remember when I was 19 or
20 um and I had a YouTube channel at the
time that was making me a few thousand
dollars a month and I remember a college
professor telling me like that's a waste
of time. That's not a real business. And
like maybe that created a chip on my
shoulder, but like back then it was like
I was 19 with a channel making more than
at a certain point I was making more
than my parents as a as a 20-year-old on
YouTube and people still were just like
this isn't real. It's not a real thing.
So, I've always been bullish on YouTube,
but I'm at a place now where I've
actually never been more bullish, which
is crazy after what I've just said. And
the reason for me is I'm just seeing it
happen. We are kind of we're like in the
1920s or 1930s of like Hollywood and TV
and like film in my opinion on YouTube
right now. I can show you some crazy
graphs which we could share with the
audience which just show the average
increase in AVD over the last five
years. not 10 years, just 5 years, and
how it's like doubling AVD, how the
platform is going from a mobile phone
platform to a TV platform. And I kind of
view it like this, like you know, I
think YouTube is the number one podcast
platform in America. Neil Mohan shared
that from YouTube, the CEO. YouTube is
going after
TV with, you know, 20, 30, 40 minute
videos on TV. They feel premium. If
anyone wants to go watch a Michelle
Carrier video, like you watch that video
and you're like, "This is like highlevel
TV and it's a YouTube YouTuber, right?
It's like Emmy award-winning level
stuff, right? And it's just a YouTuber."
So, we got podcast, we got TV. I feel
like YouTube is going after just like
traditional Hollywood as well. I think
it's interesting like two of the highest
grossing films right now are YouTubers,
right? Like Back Rooms and Obsession.
They're creators. They're just creators
and and like everyone in Hollywood is
like scrambling like how do they know
this stuff? How do they know what's
going to resonate with people? How do
they figure out how to make these ideas
go viral so people go watch the movie?
>> It's the skill, right? It's the same
skill.
>> Retention curve.
>> It's retention curves. It's retention
curves. It's understanding hype. It's
understanding virality. It's like it's
that like and same thing I said at the
start that the winner of the 2028
election might be the person who comes
up with the best viral content. like
Mandami in New York, you know,
regardless of who what you think agree
or disagree with politics, he's a
[__] G when it comes to viral
content. He's great at viral content.
So,
>> I mean, same with Trump. I mean, you
could you could argue that he went on
the right podcasts
>> 100%. That that might have swung and won
in the election,
>> you know, like a a party that got new
media and a party that didn't, right?
>> So, um yeah, I I'm really bullish on
YouTube. I think I think the platform
continues in this direction of kind of
like almost like two paths diverging
where you have like premium highly
produced content which is like you know
basically rivaling TV, Hollywood which
is already happening and you know
YouTube is the highest watch streaming
platform in the world. It's beating
Netflix. It's beating Disney. It's
beating everything else. I think that
continues to happen because they just
have the business model like they've
figured out the business model better
than anyone else where we basically
stand back. We don't put our, you know,
hands into the curation. We just say,
"Hey, we're going to enable all these
creators to go make money and go make
great content." And, you know, every
other platform that tries to like buy
that is struggling. It's it's a lot
harder. So, I think YouTube goes after
that. I think what's interesting is like
YouTube shorts, it's it is it could be
corrected if I'm wrong here, but I think
YouTube shorts is the most watched short
form platform in the world like more
than Tik Tok. It's, you know, not banned
in India, which helps.
>> YouTube even just recently announced
that they're bringing back DMs, so chat
and DMs onto YouTube, which is something
that used to be there like 15 years ago.
They got rid of it and they're bringing
it back cuz what's interesting is
recently the UK banned social media. I
don't know if you saw that,
>> but the UK banned social media for under
16s and YouTube was put into it. And I
was like, what the [__] Like YouTube is
not social media. Like social there's
nothing to be social. Like you don't
talk to your friends on YouTube. You
just watch content. It's media, right?
But there is a component where they're
starting to look back into social. So, I
think YouTube just continues to be about
who can make the best content. It's
going to continue to be long. I think in
10, 20 years, yeah, you're going to see
this divergence where there's high
quality premium content and then there
is still this like stripped back raw
authentic content as well that's like 30
40 minute rambles of a guy ranting about
something and you know, things like
that. You have your short form. Don't if
you've ever been around like the younger
generation. I'm talking like you know 10
year olds and 11 year olds or like my
friends like I was with my friend's
sister and she was she was like you want
to watch YouTube? I was like yeah sure.
She puts on YouTube puts on YouTube
starts watching this video and then
while she's watching the YouTube video
she's scrolling YouTube shorts and I'm
like
I thought you want to watch YouTube.
She's like I am.
>> She's like I'm doing both at the same
time. And I'm like damn
>> that doesn't sound healthy guys. I don't
I don't recommend that.
>> Yeah I do not recommend that.
>> Doubling down on the views for the
channel there. Both the shorts and the
longs. Yeah,
>> I actually would take a completely
different route. Again, looking under
kind of the operator lens. On the ecom
side, you are a slave to the algorithm
of these big platforms, i.e. pay for
Google ads, Meta. Everybody's looking
for the next place to spend their
dollar. There is no better place to
plant your money that goes longer and
could be chopped up and put elsewhere
than YouTube. I would argue any single
ecom operator that comes on here, where
do you get a better bang for your buck
that you win on that platform and then
you can use that content elsewhere. So,
I just think everybody is always
searching for the the next apploving,
the next universal CTV. Everybody's
looking for the next thing when it's
literally sitting right in front of you.
And if you just put the time and effort
into it, you're going to be good. Yeah.
All right, guys. So, clearly we are very
[__] passionate about YouTube. Let's
round the corner. Let's go into
Quickstre. I'm going to ask you a
million questions and see your thoughts.
>> Rapid fire.
>> Let's go. What do you think is the best
business model for a creator in 2026?
>> I still think it's
I still think it's views. I think it's
ads and and sponsors for for most
creators cuz I think if you're starting
from scratch as a creator, just having
the views and ads business is basically
just like seamless. You just turn on
AdSense, you're making money from your
videos. sponsorships, you plug in 45
seconds integrations. Like I think most
I think I would say I would make a
statement that 95% of normal creators
should just focus on that business
model. Maybe look at digital products,
but like I think that's the one because
it's seamless. Every time I see a
creator try to start a business that
doesn't have the commitment to like
doing it well and like really sending it
like and having the expertise or
bringing in a great operator, it's like
it's tricky. If you're starting with a
business though, like if you're if you
have like a a digital product, if you
have like a, you know, something like
that to sell, I think that's a different
question. Then I think that, you know,
just making great content and being able
to integrate it into the product like a
Red Bull video, like there's no point in
the Red Bull video where you go like,
oh, like make sure you buy a Red Bull.
It's like, no, they're about to do
something awesome and right before they
do something awesome, they drink a Red
Bull. It's just seamless product
placement. So, I think that's a
different question. But yeah, for most
YouTubers like I do think that just the
ads and sponsor business is just elite.
That's like phase one. Phase two is you
get that and then you you build into
like like digital products or things
that are quite seamless. Then phase
three is probably a physical business.
It's like okay, if you really want to go
like you know you've got your Mr. Beast
with Feastables, you got Ryan Train with
Joyide Candy. Like if you want to go
into like a product business, a a
consumer good business, whatever it
might be, I think that's phase three.
The key thing for me though is like
depending on the product you're selling,
everything is still downstream of the
views, right? So like this is why I I am
a view maximizer. It's like sometimes I
see these people and they just get
obsessed with these business models for
their channel, but then it's like, well,
if you were able to just get more people
in the funnel to begin with, like you
just have a bigger business anyway. So
it's like depends on what you're
selling, but like you know, if you're
selling candy,
having more people watch your video is
going to lead to more candy sales than,
you know, having a really niche candy
audience. Um, I think what's good about
it is there is an immediate model.
Obviously, AdSense can be turned on
fairly immediate. I think you need like
10,000 subs and then there's all these
different ways to kind of get low
sponsorship dollars and you could build
a real business for either zero opex or
a couple hundred,000 in cost and do a
million,2 million, 5 million in
sponsorship. So, highly profitable. Uh,
Mr. Beast, what's the one thing you
learned from him that changed how you
think about YouTube permanently?
I think you know those you know those
things where like you know that phrase
like everyone thinks they're a baller
until they meet a real baller or like
everyone thinks they're a savage until
they make a real savage.
>> Everybody thinks they're better than
Brunson until they play Brunson. Let's
go Knicks in 2026.
>> Well, I think for me it was like every
like I thought I was really bullish on
YouTube and like all in on YouTube and
like thought this was the [__] and then
I had some fun conversations with Jimmy.
I'm like holy [__] like dude he however
bullish I thought because this is a
great little point about Jimmy I would
say is I remember you know when you talk
to someone like that and they say
something and you think it's a little
diluted like this happens all the time
when you meet like like geniuses right
so I remember in 20 probably 2021 or
2020 I remember Jimmy saying like I'm
thinking about videos now that I think
can get a 100 million views in 3 years
time he said that and at the time he was
doing this is when I was working with
him he was probably doing like 25 30
million views a video still great right
but I was like 100 million views on
YouTube videos consistently. No way. I
remember saying that and this is me as a
YouTube strategist who would dedicate my
life to it, who believed and was very
optimistic. I was like, "Dude, I love
the optimism." I remember saying that to
him. I remember saying, "I love the
optimism,
dude." Like 300 million views, 400
million views, 500 million views. Like,
I think he's got I think the Squid Game
video is going to cross a billion views.
Like, so I'm like sitting there being
like, well, you know, he was right about
that. So, I think he was just more
bullish on YouTube than anything I'd
ever seen. Like I've just never met
anyone that was like, "No, you don't you
don't get it, guys. Like this is big.
This is bigger than we all think and I'm
going to get there."
>> What is the best YouTube video ever made
in your opinion and why?
>> So I think there's two I'm going to
give. The first one is Mr. Be Squid
Game. It's just like an insane
spectacle. Perfectly built on a trend,
great title, great thumbnail, you know,
so much production. I think he said he
spent5 or $6 million on that, which was
I felt like that was like a real like
turning point moment where we're like,
"Oh shit." Like he's spending like a
movie budget on a YouTube video. Like
holy [__] So I would say that one. But
another one I would pick was is actually
a video from Mark Robber called Ninja
Warrior Squirrel Obstacle Course. Have
you seen this?
>> No. Let's pop that up cuz that's
probably very very interesting.
>> It's so good. So it's such a good
YouTube video because in theory I don't
think it's like prohibitively expensive
to make. Like I think you have to have a
good skill to to do what he did. But
basically he was like sitting at home
during quarantine and he was seeing that
all these these squirrels were stealing
his bird feeder, his bird seed. So he
created a ninja warrior course for the
squirrels to get to his bird seed and he
was like, "Well, basically if they can
cross this course and get to the bird
feed bird seed, they deserve it at that
point." So he had all these squirrels
and he gave them names and they're like
going across this ninja warrior course
to then get this bird seed. And it was
just like such a good video. It did over
100 million views and I was like, it's
just great YouTube content. Like that's
that's the video that like I remember
watching that video and being like and
my dad is like, you know, 66 or
something, you know, lives in Ireland in
the countryside and he's just like, I
don't get this YouTube thing. And then I
showed him that video. He was like,
"That was good. That was really good."
And I was like, "Yeah, it's so hard to
typcast the skill set of who's good at
YouTube." Yeah.
>> Like how the [__] did he come up with
that idea? I don't I don't know.
>> He's he was a NASA engineer, which is
interesting, right? So he Mar was a NASA
engineer who left to go make YouTube
videos and I think like some some part
of his like engineery brain of like
reverse engineering. Okay, like this
worked in traditional media and total
wipeout and like you know warrior ninja
warrior like what does it look like if I
bring that over and you know do that
with you know brilliant.
>> Um what does Mr. Beast get wrong about
content creation?
>> Cook his ass boys.
>> Does Mr. going to be wrong.
Like, let me think out loud.
>> We're actually not going to cut this
part out. [laughter]
>> Yeah, that would be a funny little
>> It is. It is.
>> Uh,
I it's it's hard like I I think I think
as like in terms of what he is trying to
do, nothing like he is trying to be the
big he is. If if I said earlier in the
podcast, I'm a view maximizer. It's like
that thing, everyone's a baller till
they make a meet a real baller.
Everyone's a max a view maximizer until
they meet Mr. Beast. It's like, okay,
like I think he is just so prioritized
on views at all costs that you could
make the argument that there is value in
sometimes, not getting the 200 million
view video, but making an audience feel
more connected to you or showing more
personality. I think Jimmy is a really
interesting person and actually has lots
of layers to his personality that I
think I'd love to see him show more in
his videos. Like I think there's more
Jimmy that I think he could show in his
videos.
>> Uh so you said you schedule five hours a
week studying YouTube videos. What does
that actually look like? What are you
doing in those five hours?
>> So one of the smartest things I did
early in my career was I created
playlists on my YouTube account. And I
created playlist. I just titled them
like outlier video, cool title,
thumbnail retention, right? Each week I
watch YouTube anyway, like we all do,
right? And whenever I see something I
like, I add it to the playlist. So, if I
see like a viral video, add to my
outlier playlist. If I see a really good
intro, add to my intro playlist. If I
see a really good thumbnail, add to my
thumbnail playlist. Then, what I'll do
is have time scheduled each week where
I'll just go through and I'll watch
those videos and I'll just take notes on
what I liked or what I didn't like and
you take ideas. So, quite often I'll be
in conversation and someone's like, "How
did you think of that idea for the
thumbnail?" It's like, "Oh, let me show
you my playlist from three years ago
where I put that in." You know, it's
like that's been the thing that's helped
me the most. So, I I take all these
videos, put them in playlists, and then
each week I'll have 3 to five hour
schedule where I'm just like literally
just watching YouTube. Like my job is to
watch YouTube and study what's working.
>> Um, we're just going to pop up Patty in
2026 and then Patty in 2026 with an MCP
where you can use all the data and all
the stuff that you like last 3, five, 10
years. It's going to be on steroids.
Dude, what is the hardest part of your
job that nobody sees? I
>> I think I think the hardest part is
doing it consistently. So, you know, I
am not that impressed when someone makes
a viral video. I'm impressed when
someone makes a viral video again and
again and again in multiple niches. And
the reason I'm so bullish on myself and
my team is right now like we have an
entertainment channel, sports channel,
wildlife channel. We've worked with
finance channels, we've worked with
education channels, learning channels.
Like we've worked in so many different
niches all the way from Yeah. like
astrophotography to like a rebel, right?
And if you can consistently go viral, I
think that is that is the skill. Like
that is the most important skill. So I
think the hardest part is just being
able to do it again and again and again.
Like I don't think it would be that
difficult for me to sign a client and be
like, "Look, give me a month and I'll
blow up your your channel with a video."
Done it all the time. Done that so many
times in my career. The hard part is
doing that and being like, "We're going
to work together for three years and
grow the biggest channel in the niche."
And we don't sign a client unless we
think we can grow them to be the biggest
channel in their niche. That's our like
kind of framework. It's like we want
even if that niche is small. If that
niche is like we are a small niche that
teaches you how to like build systems in
ClickUp, right? I'm like, okay, let's be
the biggest ClickUp systems channel on
YouTube, then [__] it. Let's do it.
Right? So, I think the hardest thing is
just being able to do it consistently. A
lot of people flash in the pan. They can
make a viral video here and there. It's
great. But like just like in sport, in
business, in anything, it's the people
that just do it again and again that you
respect the most.
>> Ironically, we're big ClickUp guys here.
That's a great transition to the last
question before the final four. Why
would you quit?
>> If I would quit if I felt that the game
of YouTube was becoming less of a
meritocracy and more focused on the
traditional gatekeeping that Hollywood
and all these different things became
known for. So I think the thing I've
always loved about YouTube is I am a kid
from nothing in the middle of Ireland
who no one ever heard of in my bedroom
and I could make videos that people all
around the world could see. Like that's
always been the thing I've been
fascinated by by there was no like no
one knows my dad, no one knows my
mother, like no I wasn't connected to
anyone. I just made good videos and it
resonated and built my career. If I felt
like there was a point in the future
where gatekeeping was coming back in,
it's like oh like you know the big guys
like are holding it and like you know
making sure that only only their videos
get shown or stuff like that. Then it
just doesn't become a sport anymore and
it becomes a game of politics and all
that sort of stuff and I just don't I
can't deal with that. I've had one 9 to5
in my life. Couldn't do it. Couldn't do
it. I can't deal with like having sort
of like a boss for politics or stuff
like that. So, I think if YouTube
changed in that way I would stop.
There's nothing financially I hit my
financial number probably two years ago
that I always wanted and I still work
harder now than I've ever worked before.
So, it's nothing financial. It's purely
like if the game is not as true as it is
right now, I'm not playing it.
>> Love that.
>> Um, all right. Last four questions that
I ask everybody. Favorite book or
podcast and why?
I think the podcast that had the biggest
influence on me. I'm sure a lot of
people can relate to this is Naval. The
first time he went on Joe Rogan, have
you have you listened to that podcast?
>> Of course, bro. That his book is
Almanac. Will pop that book up. So many
people have mentioned that book. He is
it's also like everything is just so
everything he says is just brilliant and
it's like yeah, it's like he's a mini
Wikipedia. The Williamson episode was
good as well too. He doesn't go on that
many podcasts. That's one of I probably
have I don't know 10 and one of them has
already been on 10 guests that I really
really want on. He's definitely one of
them.
>> And I I think his like principles and
how he thinks about things actually like
relate to so many spaces, right? Just
like how we talk about virality like
translates to so many spaces. It's like
you know I think if you if you have like
a car valet business, you can still
learn from Naval. So I think his his
episode was amazing. I actually met Eric
who wrote that book as well. He's
>> Jorgensson.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's so funny you say that
too because I was thinking in my brain
too. I was actually going to say that is
such a big Tam. Like you could take all
of his stuff and like my mom, my dad, my
wife, everybody, anybody can take these
these principles and frameworks and put
it to mentally, physically, anything.
>> 100%. I also really like the book zero
to one, Peter Theel. Yeah,
>> that was a banger when I read that
because like just like the his thoughts
on like monopolies and like operating in
a market of one and like I do think
especially when any space becomes more
competitive which YouTube is becoming
right now like being able to sort of
view yourself as a market of one and
thinking like what are my moes what are
my monopolies on content basically that
I can play on is really important.
>> Shout out to Blake Masters. He wrote the
forward in that book. He's a homie and
watcher of this podcast. Great book.
Arizona guy when I lived in Arizona. All
right. Entrepreneur or creator that you
want to give flowers to and why?
>> So, I think, you know, especially being
on a podcast and being on a podcast like
this, which is which is great and
incredible production value, making me
think of my friend Chris Williamson in
Austin. Like, he's just someone from
spending some time around. I'm like,
dude, he gets YouTube. He's so
committed. Like, there I think one thing
you probably relate to this, but like
when you grow in your career, the most
difficult thing becomes avoiding the
woman in the red dress and all the shiny
objects and stuff like that.
>> Tough. Yeah, if you're someone like
Chris, like you're getting like pulled
in a million directions, so many things,
whatever. Every time I catch up with
him, he's like, "Dude, I just filmed
this podcast. It's [__] amazing.
Here's the tile. Here's the thumbnail."
And he's just like on, we're at dinner.
He's on Slack like looking at the tiles
and thumbnails. He's just like, I'm
like, "That is that's you can't train
that. It's just like another level of
like intensity."
>> I just had an hour conversation with
Luke Betts, his partner on Newtonic.
>> Yeah. And Luke was telling me some uh
>> it made me feel less psycho because
obviously I take this very very
seriously and hearing some of the stuff
that he does.
>> Yeah. I got a lot of respect for what
he's done, especially from a production
perspective. And like,
yeah, I feel like a lot of these kind of
principles and frameworks that you
talked about, he has them kind of
embedded in his brain. Um,
how big can Patty Galloway be?
>> I think I am 5% of the way to my
potential. I think if I'm being
completely frank and honest with myself,
I think I work really hard and I'm, you
know, doing really well, but there's so
much I haven't covered and like done.
Like I think for example, right now like
we have 5 to 10 clients, you know,
that's all we work with, right? I just
post tweets and go on podcasts, right?
And I've I've got to that point and
I've, you know,ve I've like got to a
point where I do really well. Well, I
have these businesses and whatever, but
like for me, the next 5 years, I turned
30 and what I was expecting is I was
expecting to turn 30 and be like, "Okay,
look, financially, I'm pretty good.
Like, I've never really wanted that much
anyway. I'm not too like material. I've
always been like more about the process
and and mastering a thing." But like,
you know, I'm I'm fine. I could chill. I
can coast, you know? And I was sort of
sitting there and it was like an
interesting thing. I saw this really
good tweet from a guy called Matt
Pollson. you know, Matt, and he said
something like, you know, everyone
thinks the hardest years of business is
like the first two or three years where
you're trying to make things work. It's
really difficult. He's like, I disagree.
I think the hardest years of business is
like years five, six, and seven because
things are working and complacency
starts to creep in and you start to
start to look in the mirror and say, do
I really want this? Right? And I had
that moment when I turned 30 just a few
months ago where I was like, look, I've
done everything I want to do. I've grown
in the space. I've, you know, done
amazing things. like am I in a place
where I just want to sort of coast or am
I in a place where I want to lock in and
I was just like thinking about it I took
a week I went to Arizona actually stayed
in Paradise Valley with Sedona had a
great time and I came home and I was
like I am going to [__] lock in like
I do not think I have provided the world
anywhere near as much value as I can
like I have provided a lot of value for
some people really you know including
myself and of course but like I think I
can do a lot more and I think I can grow
a lot more channels. I think I can have
a lot more impact. And like I said, I
think I do think, of course, I'm going
to be bullish on myself, but I do think
media, politics, sport. Here's a great
example. Do you know who Ozaral is? I
probably butchered his pronunciation,
but Ozaral is a player for Spain, the
team who are the favorites to win the
World Cup. He scored two goals in his
last game. He's also one of the best
players in La Liga. You've probably
never heard of him. Most people have
never heard of him. and he is an
absolutely unbelievable player, but
there's probably players on his team
that make more money than him in one
social media post than he does in like 6
months of being a professional
footballer. And I think it just came it
comes down to a simple fact which is
like attention and like
content and these things like Lamin Mal
has a YouTube channel. I don't know if
you've seen it, but Lamin, who's like
the super super kid from Spain, he's 18.
He has a YouTube channel. He's doing
like 5 10 million views a video. Neymar
just launched his YouTube channel. I
think the thing for me is like
this skill is it's it's entering so many
spaces. I should be able to like use my
skill in these spaces more. I feel like,
you know, I've done a great job, but I
think there's so much more I could do
with like sport, business, brands, maybe
even politics, but like, you know,
there's so many areas I could use my
skill for more good. Like I think in the
in the space of creators as well, most
businesses that are built on the space
are built on an existing audience,
right? So I think about like a talent
agency or like you know a brand
management or like production company.
All these things, they're really
valuable. They're really important, but
they're all built on something that
already exists, right? The audience that
already exists. My company and me, we we
are the ones that are working at the
front of that funnel. We're like
actually building the audience that
exists for the whole space potentially,
but we're we haven't reached scale yet.
It's hard for me to find people that are
as as good. Like I said earlier, my my
number two guy in my company for for
Outlier is a former YouTuber with over a
million subscribers, you know, and he's
a genius. And it's like there's only so
many people like that you can convince
to come work for you and stuff like
that. But when I fix my my my scale
problem there, I think I can be so much
bigger. So, I think I'm 5 or 10% of the
way of where I want to be.
>> Completely agree, man. Absolutely
amazing episode. I appreciate you
sharing so much wisdom. We're gonna do a
special shout out to Baby Pacino, his
dog. 5 million views, 100,000 followers
on Instagram went very fast. Perfect
example that he can scale any niche, any
channel, anything. YouTube is the
playbook and tons and tons of PDFs down
below for free that's going to help you
guys on the journey to scale on YouTube.
And dude, we got to do this again.
Amazing time.
>> 100%. Thank you so much, man.
>> Thank you guys so much for watching. If
you got value out of this episode, every
single [music] principle, framework,
tactic is in one free playbook linked at
the top of the description. Grab it, hit
subscribe, and we'll see you in the next
one.